Consumers and adapters

Now, we will see some examples that show why iterators are so useful. Iterators are lazy and have to be activated by invoking a consumer to start using the values. Let's start with a range of the numbers from 0 to 999 included. To make this into a vector, we apply the function collect() consumer:

// see code in Chapter 5/code/adapters_consumers.rs 
let rng = 0..1000; 
let rngvec: Vec<i32> = rng.collect(); 
// alternative notation: 
// let rngvec = rng.collect::<Vec<i32>>(); 
println!("{:?}", rngvec); 

This prints out the range (we shortened the output with...):

    [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, ... , 999] 

The function collect() loops through the entire iterator, collecting all of the elements into a container, here of type Vec<i32>. That container does not have to be an iterator. Notice that we indicate the item type of the vector with Vec<i32>, but we could have also written it as Vec<_>. The notation collect::<Vec<i32>>() is new, it indicates that the function collect() is a parametrized method that can work with generic types. See the next section for more information.

The function find() consumer gets the first value of the iterator that makes its condition (here >= 42) true and returns it as a value of the type Option, for example:

let forty_two = rng.find(|n| *n >= 42); 
println!("{:?}", forty_two);  // 

This prints out the following output:

    Some(42)

The value of the function find() is of type Option because the condition could be false for all items and then it would return a None value. The condition is wrapped in a closure |n| *n >= 42, which is applied on every item of the iterator through a reference n; that's why we have to dereference *n to get the value.

Suppose we only want the even numbers in our range, producing a new range by testing a closure condition on each item. This can be done with the filter() function, which is an adapter because it produces a new iterator from the old one. Its result can be collected just like any iterator:

let rng_even = rng.filter(|n| is_even(*n)) 
                  .collect::<Vec<i32>>(); // (1)
println!("{:?}", rng_even); 

Here, is_even is the following function:

fn is_even(n: i32) -> bool { 
    n % 2 == 0 
} 

This prints out the following output:

    [0, 2, 4, ..., 996, 998] 

This shows that odd integers are filtered out.

Notice how we can chain our consumers and adapters, just apply collect() on the result of the filter() function with .collect(), as in the previous line 1.

What if we want to cube (n * n * n) every item in the resulting iterator? Producing a new range by applying a closure to each item in it can be done with the map() function:

let rng_even_pow3 = rng.filter(|n| is_even(*n)) 
                       .map(|n| n * n * n) 
                       .collect::<Vec<i32>>(); 
println!("{:?}", rng_even_pow3); 

This prints out the following output:

    [0, 8, 64, ..., 988047936, 994011992]  

If you only want the first five results, insert a take(5) adapter before the collect. The resulting vector then contains the following:

    [0, 8, 64, 216, 512]  

So, call a consumer if you see the following message while compiling:

warning: unused result which must be used: iterator adaptors are lazy and do nothing unless consumed  

To see all consumers and adapters, consult the docs of module std::iter.

Exercise:

Another very powerful consumer is the fold() function.
The following example calculates the sum of the first hundred integers. It starts with a base value 0, which is also the initial value of the accumulator sum, and then iterates and adds every item n to sum:
let sum = (0..101).fold(0, |sum, n| sum + n);
println!("{}", sum); //prints out 5050

Now calculate the product of all cubes of the integers in the range from 1 to 6.
The result should be 1728000; watch out for the base value! As a second exercise, subtract all items from the following array [1, 9, 2, 3, 14, 12] starting from 0 (that is, 0 -1 -9 -2 and so on).
This should result in 41 (for example code, see Chapter 5/exercises/fold.rs).

Static and dynamic dispatch

Our function sqroot from the previous section is generic and works for any Float type. The compiler creates a different executable sqroot method for any type it is supposed to work with, in this case the f32 and f64 type. Rust applies this mechanism when a function call is polymorphic, that is when a function can accept arguments of different type. This is called static dispatch (also called compile-time polymorphism) and there is no runtime overhead involved. This is in contrast to how Java interfaces work, where the dispatching is done dynamically in runtime by the JVM. However Rust also has a form of dynamic dispatch (also called runtime polymorphism), using so called trait objects.

For an example of static and dynamic dispatch, see the following code snippet:

// see code in Chapter 6/code/dispatch.rs 
struct Circle; 
struct Triangle; 
 
trait Figure { 
    fn print(&self); 
} 
 
impl Figure for Circle { 
    fn print(&self) { 
        println!("Circle"); 
    } 
} 
 
impl Figure for Triangle { 
    fn print(&self) { 
        println!("Triangle"); 
    } 
} 
 
// static dispatch with trait bounds 
fn log<T: Figure>(figure: &T) { 
    figure.print(); 
} 
 
// dynamic dispatch: function takes a trait object 
fn logd(figure: &Figure) { 
    figure.print(); 
} 
 
fn main() { 
// static dispatch 
    let circle   = Circle; 
    let triangle = Triangle; 
     
    log(&circle); 
    log(&triangle); 
 
// dynamic dispatch:  
    let mut figures: Vec*Box*Figure** = Vec::new(); 
    figures.push(Box::new(Circle)); 
    figures.push(Box::new(Triangle)); 
     
    // the precise type of figure can only be known at runtime: 
    for figure in figures { 
        logd(&*figure); 
    } 
} 

This produces the following output:

    Circle
    Triangle
    Circle
    Triangle  

With static dispatch, there is a compiled version for each specific type for which the function is called. These calls can be inlined, which guarantees the best performance. On the other hand the binary code size is increased. Dynamic dispatch is used when the precise type on which a function is called can only be known at runtime. In our example the trait object is a reference to an instance implementing the Figure trait. Because calls are resolved at runtime, dynamic dispatch is not so performant as its static variant, but sometimes there is no other option.

More detailed info can be found at https://doc.rust-lang.org/1.0.0-beta/book/static-and-dynamic-dispatch.html.

What this book covers

Chapter 1, Starting with Rust, discusses the main reasons that led to the development of Rust. We compare Rust with other languages and indicate the areas for which it is most appropriate. Then, we guide you through installing all the necessary components for a Rust development environment. In particular, you will learn how to work with Cargo, Rust’s package manager.

Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types, looks at the basic structure of a Rust program. We discuss the primitive types, how to declare variables and whether they have to be typed, and the scope of variables. Immutability, one of the key cornerstones of Rust’s safety strategy is also illustrated. Then, we look at basic operations, how to do formatted printing, and the important difference between expressions and statements.

Chapter 3, Using Functions and Control Structures, shows how to define functions, and the different ways to influence program execution flow in Rust. We also take a look at attributes and how to do testing in Rust.

Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns, discusses the basic data types for programming, such as strings, vectors, slices, tuples, and enums. You will learn how to get input from the console and how to work with program arguments. Then we show you the powerful pattern matching that is possible in Rust and how values are extracted by destructuring patterns.

Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling, explores the functional features of Rust. We see how data structures and functions can be defined in a generic way. Furthermore, you will learn how to work with Rust’s unique error-handling mechanism.

Chapter 6, Using Traits and OOP in Rust, explores the object-oriented features of Rust. We see how traits can be used to define behavior and to simulate inheritance in data structures. We also explore some common OOP patterns implemented in Rust, such as the visitor and the builder pattern.

Chapter 7, Ensuring Memory Safety and Pointers, exposes the borrow checker, Rust’s mechanism to ensure that only memory safe operations can occur during program execution. Different kinds of pointers are discussed in this chapter.

Chapter 8, Organizing Code and Macros, discusses the bigger code-organizing structures in Rust, such as modules and crates. It also touches upon how to build macros in order to generate code, thus saving time and effort.

Chapter 9, Concurrency – Coding for Multicore Execution, delves into Rust’s concurrency model based on threads and channels. We also discuss a safe strategy for working with shared mutable data.

Chapter 10, Programming at the Boundaries, looks at how Rust behaves in situations where we have to leave the safety boundaries, such as when interfacing with C or using raw pointers, and how Rust minimizes potential dangers when doing so.

Chapter 11, Exploring the Standard Library, gives us an overview of what is contained in Rust’s Standard Library with an emphasis on collections and the built-in macros. We also discuss how to let Rust work without standard library, for example, in very resource-constrained environments.

Chapter 12, The Ecosystem of Crates, covers how to work with crates built by other developers. We look at crates to work with files and databases, do web development, and develop graphics applications and games.

Generic data structures and functions

Genericity is the capacity to write code once, with types not or partly specified, so that the code can be used for many different types. Rust has this capacity in abundance, applying it for both data structures and functions.

A composite data structure is generic if the type of its items can be of a general type <T>. The type T can for example be an i32 value, an f64, a String, but also a struct type like Person that we have coded ourselves. So, we can have a vector Vec<f64>, but also a vector Vec<Person>. If you make T a concrete type, then you must substitute the type T with that type everywhere T appears in the definition of the data structure.

Our data structure can be parametrized with a generic type <T>, and so has multiple concrete definitions--it is polymorphic. Rust makes extensive use of this concept, which we encountered already in Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns when we talked about arrays, vectors, slices and the Result and Option types.

Suppose you want to define a struct with two fields, first and second, but you want to keep the type of these fields generic. We can define it as follows:

// see code in Chapter 5/code/generics.rs 
struct Pair<T> { 
    first: T, 
    second: T, 
} 

We can now define a Pair of magic numbers, or a Pair of magicians, or whatever we want, like this:

let magic_pair: Pair<u32> = Pair { first: 7, second: 42 }; 
let pair_of_magicians: Pair<&str> = Pair { first: "Gandalf", second: "Sauron" }; 

What if we wanted to write functions that work with generic data structures? They would also have to be generic, right? As a simple example, how would we write a function that returns the second item of a Pair? We can do it like this:

fn second<T>(pair: Pair<T>) { 
  pair.second; 
} 

We could also call the second function as follows:

let a = second(magic_pair); 

This produces the following output:

    42  

Note the type <T> right after the function name second; this is how generic functions are declared.

Let's now investigate why Option and Result types are so powerful. Here is the definition of the Option type again:

enum Option<T> { 
    Some(T), 
 None 
} 

From this, we can define multiple concrete types, as follows:

let x: Option<i8> = Some(5); 
let pi: Option<f64> = Some(3.14159265359); 
let none: Option<f64> = None; 
let none2 = None::<f64>; 
let name: Option<&str> = Some("Joyce"); 

When the type does not correspond with the value, a mismatched types error occurs, as in the following code:

let magic: Option<f32> = Some(42) 

We can define a struct Person as follows:

struct Person { 
  name: &'static str, 
  id:   i32 
} 

Then, we can add a few Person objects using let binding:

let p1 = Person{name: "James Bond", id: 7}; 
let p2 = Person{name: "Vin Diesel", id: 12}; 
let p3 = Person{name: "Robin Hood", id: 42}; 

Then, we can make an Option type value or a vector for the struct Person as the following:

let op1: Option<Person> = Some(p1); 
let pvec: Vec<Person> = vec![p2, p3]; 

You would use the Option type in a situation where you expect to get a value, but when there is always a possibility that no value will be given. A typical scenario would be user input.

Shared mutable states

How can we make the not_shared.rs program give us the correct result? Rust provides tools, such as atomic types from the submodule std::sync::atomic, to handle shared mutable state safely. In order to share data, you need to wrap the data in some of these sync primitives, such as Arc, Mutex, RwLock, AtomicUSize, and so on.

Basically, the principle of locking is used, as in operating systems and database systems. Exclusive access to a resource is given to the thread that has obtained a lock (also called a mutex, from mutually exclusive) on the resource. A lock can only be obtained by one thread at a time. In this way, two threads cannot change this resource at the same time, so no data races can occur; locking atomicity is enforced when required. When the thread that has acquired the lock has done its work, the lock is removed and another thread can then work with the data.

In Rust, this is done with the generic Mutex<T> type from the std::sync module. The sync comes from synchronize, which is exactly what we want to do with our threads.

The Mutex ensures that only one thread at a time can change the contents of our data.

We must make an instance of this type, wrapping our data like this:

// code from Chapter 9/code/thread_safe.rs:   
use std::sync::{Arc, Mutex};
 let data = Mutex::new(health); 
Now, within the for loop immediately after that, we spawn the new thread, and we place a lock on the health object: 
     for i in 2..5 {  
thread::spawn(move || { 
            let mut health = data.lock().unwrap(); 
            // do other things 
         } 
     } 

The call to lock() will return a reference to the value inside the Mutex, and it will block any other calls to lock() until that reference goes out of scope, which is at the end of the thread closure. Then the thread has done its work and the lock is automatically removed. But for now, we will still get an error: capture of moved value: 'data'. This is because the data variable cannot be moved to another thread multiple times.

This problem can be solved by using an equivalent of the Rc pointer from Chapter 7, Ensuring Memory Safety and Pointers, in the Reference counting section. Indeed, the situation is very similar: all the threads need a reference to the same data, our health variable. So we apply the same techniques from Chapter 6, ;Using Traits and OOP in Rust here: make an Rc pointer to point to our data, and make a clone() of the pointer for each reference that is needed. But a simple Rc pointer is not thread-safe, therefore we need a special version of it that is thread-safe, the so-called atomic reference counted pointer, or Arc<T>. Atomic means it is safe across threads, and it is also generic.

So, we envelop our health variable inside an Arc pointer, like this:

  let data = Arc::new(Mutex::new(health)); 

And in the for loop, we make a new pointer to the Mutex with clone:

  for i in 2..5 { 
      let mutex = data.clone(); 
      thread::spawn(move || {  
               let mut health = mutex.lock().unwrap(); 
            *health *= i; 
}); 
  } 

Each thread now works with a copy of the pointer obtained by clone(). The Arc instance will keep track of the number of references to health. A call to clone() will increment the reference count on health. The mutex reference goes out of scope at the end of the thread closure, which will decrement the reference count. Arc will free the associated health resource when that reference count is zero.

Calling lock() gives the active thread exclusive access to the data. In principle, acquiring the lock might fail, so it returns a Result<T, E> object. In the preceding code, we assume everything is OK. unwrap() is a quick means to return a reference to the data, but in a failure case, it panics.

Quite a few steps were involved here, so we will repeat the code in its entirety here, this time providing robust error handling to replace unwrap(). Digest each line with the explanations given previously:

// code from Chapter 9/code/thread_safe.rs: 
use std::thread; 
use std::sync::{Arc, Mutex}; 
 
fn main() { 
   let mut health = 12; 
   println!("health before: {:?}", health); 
   let data = Arc::new(Mutex::new(health)); 
   for i in 2..5 { 
        let mutex = data.clone(); 
        thread::spawn(move || { 
            let health = mutex.lock(); 
            match health { 
                // health is multiplied by i: 
Ok(mut health) => *health *= i, 
                Err(str) => println!("{}", str) 
            } 
        }).join().unwrap(); 
    }; 
    health = *data.lock().unwrap(); 
    println!("health after: {:?}", health); 
} 

This prints out the following:

health before: 12
health after: 288

(Indeed, 288 = 12 * 2 * 3 * 4)

We join() the threads to give them time to do their work; data is a reference, so we need to dereference it to obtain the health value:

health = *data.lock().unwrap(); 

The mechanism outlined previously, using a combined Mutex and Arc, is advisable when the shared data occupies a significant amount of memory, because with an Arc, the data will no longer be copied for each thread. The Arc acts as a reference to the shared data and only this reference is shared and cloned.

Printing with string interpolation

An obvious way to use variables is to print out their value, as is done here:

// see Chapter 2/code/constants2.rs 
static MAX_HEALTH: i32 = 100; 
static GAME_NAME: &str = "Monster Attack"; 
const MYPI: f32 = 3.14; 
 
fn main() { 
  println!("The Game you are playing is called {}.", GAME_NAME); 
  println!("You start with {} health points.", MAX_HEALTH); 
} 

This gives an output which looks like this:

The Game you are playing is called Monster Attack.
You start with 100 health points.

The first argument of the println! macro is a literal format string containing a placeholder {}. The value of the constant or variable after the comma is converted to a string and comes in its place. There can be more than one placeholder and they can be numbered in order, so that they can be used repeatedly, as in the following code:

println!("In the Game {0} you start with {1} % health, yes you read it correctly: {1} points!", GAME_NAME, MAX_HEALTH); 

This produces the following output:

In the Game Monster Attack you start with 100 % health, yes you read it correctly: 100 points!
  

The placeholder can also contain one or more named arguments, like this:

println!("You have {points} % health", points = 70); 

This produces the following output:

You have 70 % health  

Special ways of formatting can be indicated inside the {} after a colon (:), optionally prefixed by a position, like this:

println!("MAX_HEALTH is {:x} in hexadecimal", MAX_HEALTH); // 

This gives an output like this: 64

println!("MAX_HEALTH is {:b} in binary", MAX_HEALTH);   // 

This gives an output like this: 1100100

println!( "Two written in binary is {0:b}", 2);   // 

This gives an output like this: 10

println!("pi is {:e} in floating point notation", PI);  // 

This gives an output like this: 3.14e0.

The following formatting possibilities exist:

o: For octal
x: For lower hexadecimal
X: For upper hexadecimal
p: For a pointer
b: For binary
e: For lower exponential notation
E: For upper exponential notation
?: For debugging purposes

The format! macro has the same parameters and works the same way as the println! macro, but it returns a string instead of printing out.

Consult http://doc.rust-lang.org/std/fmt/ for an overview of all possibilities.

Preface

Rust is a stable, open source, and compiled programming language that finally promises software developers the utmost safety--not only type safety, but also memory safety. The compiler carefully checks all uses of variables and pointers so that common problems from C/C++ and other languages, such as pointers to wrong memory locations or null references, are a thing of the past. Possible problems are detected at compilation time, and Rust programs execute at speeds comparable with their C++ counterparts.

Rust runs with a very light runtime, which does not perform garbage collection. Again, the compiler takes care of generating the code that frees all resources at the right time. This means Rust can run in very constrained environments, such as embedded or real-time systems. The built-in safety also guarantees concurrency without data-race problems.

It is clear that Rust is applicable in all use cases where until now C and C++ were the preferred languages and that it will do a better job at it, at least with regard to safety and robustness.

Rust is also a very rich language: it has concepts (such as immutability by default) and constructs (such as traits) that enable developers to write code in a high-level functional and object-oriented style.

The original goal of Rust was to serve as the language for writing a new safe browser engine, devoid of the many security flaws that plague existing browsers such as the Servo project from Mozilla Research.

The goal of this book is to give you a firm foundation for starting to develop in Rust. Throughout the book, we emphasize the three pillars of Rust: safety, performance, and sound concurrency. We will discuss where Rust differs from other programming languages and why this is the case. The code examples are not chosen ad hoc, but they are oriented as part of an ongoing project for building a game so that there is a sense of cohesion and evolution in the examples.

Throughout the book, I will urge you to learn by following along by typing in the code, making the requested modifications, compiling, testing, and working out the exercises.

Tuples

If you want to combine a certain number of values of different types, then you can collect them in a tuple, enclosed between parentheses (( )) and separated by commas, like this:

// from Chapter 4/code/tuples.rs 
let thor = ("Thor", true, 3500u32); 
println!("{:?}", thor); // ("Thor", true, 3500) 

The type of thor is (&str, bool, u32), that is, the tuple of the item's types.

To extract an item on index use a dot syntax:

println!("{} - {} - {}", thor.0, thor.1, thor.2); 

Another way to extract items to other variables is by destructuring the tuple:

let (name, _, power) = thor; 
println!("{} has {} power points ", name, power); 

This prints out the following output:

    Thor has 3500 power points  

Here the let statement matches the pattern on the left with the right-hand side. The _ indicates that we are not interested in the second item of thor.

Tuples can only be assigned to one another or compared with each other if they are of the same type. A one-element tuple needs to be written like this:

let one = (1,); 

A function that needs to return some values of different types can collect them in a tuple and return that tuple, like this:

fn increase_power(name: &str, power: u32) 
-> (&str, u32) { 
if power > 1000 { 
 return (name, power * 3); 
} else { 
 return (name, power * 2); 
 } 
} 

This function header could also be written as:

fn increase_power2((name, power): (&str, u32)) -> (&str, u32) 

If we call this with the following statement:

let (god, strength) = increase_power(thor.0, thor.2); 
println!("This god {} has now strength {} ", god, strength); 

The output looks like the following:

    This god Thor has now strength 10500  

A tuple is also very handy when swapping two variables:

let mut n = 0; 
let mut m = 1; 
let (n, m) = (m, n); 
println!("n: {} m: {}", n, m);

Exercise:
(see code in Chapter 4/exercises/tuples_ex.rs)
Try to compare the tuples (2, 'a') and (5, false), explain the error message.
Try to change an item in a tuple (hint: you must add a keyword for it to work).
Make an empty tuple.
Haven't we encountered this before? So the unit value is in fact an empty tuple!

The ecosystem of crates

Compared to other languages, you will see that there is a tendency in Rust to move functionalities out of the core language into their own crates. It serves to keep the standard library small, thereby reducing the size of compiled apps. This is done, for example, for working with dates and times (see next section), or for providing special concurrency primitives.

An ever-growing ecosystem of crates for Rust is at your disposal at https://crates.io/, with nearing 11,000 crates in stock at the time of writing (Sep 2017). This repository site is also a showcase, because it is written in Rust! You can search for crates on specific keywords or categories, or browse them alphabetically or on the number of downloads. Find their documentation at http://docs.rs.

At Awesome Rust (https://github.com/rust-unofficial/awesome-rust), you can find a curated list of Rust projects; this site only contains useful and stable projects, and indicates whether they compile against the latest Rust version.

The Rust Cookbook (https://rust-lang-nursery.github.io/rust-cookbook/) provides a growing set of code recipes using common crates.

In general, it is advisable that you search for crates that are already available whenever you embark on a project that requires specific functionality. There is a good chance that a crate that conforms to your needs already exists, or perhaps you can find some usable starting code upon which to build exactly what you need. Take into consideration the number of downloads and when the crate was last updated; a popular and actively updated crate is most likely of higher quality.

The trifecta of Rust - safe, fast, and concurrent

Rust is not a revolutionary language with new cutting-edge features, but it incorporates a lot of proven techniques from older languages, while massively improving upon the design of C++ in matters of safe programming.

The Rust developers designed Rust to be a general purpose and multi-paradigm language; like C++, it is an imperative, structured and object-oriented language. Besides that, it inherits a lot from functional languages on the one hand, while also incorporating advanced techniques for concurrent programming on the other hand.

The typing of variables is static (because Rust is compiled) and strong. However, unlike in Java or C++, the developer is not forced to indicate types for everything; the Rust compiler is able to infer types in many cases.

C and C++ applications are known to be haunted by problems that often lead to program crashes or memory leaks, and which are notoriously difficult to debug and solve. Think about dangling pointers, buffer overflows, null pointers, segmentation faults, data races, and so on. The Rust compiler (called rustc) is very intelligent and can detect all these problems while compiling your code, thereby guaranteeing memory safety during execution. This is done by the compiler, retaining complete control over memory layout, but without needing the runtime burden of garbage collection (see Chapter 6, Using Traits and OOP in Rust). Of course, safety also implies much less possibility for security breaches.

Rust compiles to native code like Go and Julia but, in contrast to the other two, Rust needs no runtime with garbage collection. In this respect, it also differs from Java and the languages that run on the JVM, like Scala and Clojure. Most other popular modern languages, like .NET with C# and F#, JavaScript, Python, Ruby, Dart, and so on, all need a virtual machine and garbage collection for their execution.

Rust provides several mechanisms for concurrency and parallelism. The Standard Library gives a model that works with threads to perform work in parallel, where each thread maps to an operating system thread. They do not share heap memory, but communicate data through channels and data races are eliminated by the type system (see Chapter 8, Organizing Code and Macros). If needed in your project, several crates provide an actor-model approach with lightweight threads. These mechanisms make it easy for programmers to leverage the power of the many CPU cores available on current and future computing platforms.

The rustc compiler is completely self-hosted, which means it is written in Rust and can compile itself by using a previous version. It uses the LLVM compiler framework as its backend (for more info, see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LLVM), and produces natively executable code that runs blazingly fast, because it compiles to the same low-level code as C++ ( see some benchmarks at http://benchmarksgame.alioth.debian.org/u64q/rust.php).

Rust is designed to be as portable as C++ and to run on widely-used hardware and software platforms. At present, it runs on Linux, macOS X, Windows, FreeBSD, Android, and iOS. For a more complete overview of where Rust can run, see https://forge.rust-lang.org/platform-support.html.

Rust can call C code as simply and efficiently as calling C code from C itself, and, conversely C code can also call Rust code (see Chapter 9, Concurrency - Coding for Multicore Execution).

Rust developers are called rustaceans.

Other Rust characteristics that will be discussed, in more detail in the later chapters are as follows:

Variables are immutable by default (see Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types)
Enums (see Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns)
Pattern matching (see also Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns)
Generics (see Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling)
Higher-order functions and closures (see also Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling)
An interface system called traits (see Chapter 6, Using Traits and OOP in Rust)
A hygienic macro system (see Chapter 8, Organizing Code and Macros)
Zero-cost abstractions, which means that Rust has higher-language constructs, but these do not have an impact on performance

In conclusion, Rust gives you ultimate power over memory allocation, as well as removing many security and stability problems commonly associated with native languages.

Reference counting

Sometimes you need several references to an immutable value at the same time, this is also called shared ownership. The pointer type Box<T> can't help us out here, because this type has a single owner by definition. For this, Rust provides the generic reference counted box Rc<T>, where multiple references can share the same resource. The std::rc module provides a way to share ownership of the same value between different Rc pointers; the value remains alive as long as there is least one pointer referencing it.

In the following example, we have Aliens that have a number of tentacles. Each Tentacle is also a struct instance and has to indicate to which Alien it belongs; besides that it has other properties like a degree of poison. A first attempt at this could be the following code which however does not compile:

// see Chapter 7/code/refcount_not_good.rs): 
struct Alien { 
    name: String, 
    n_tentacles: u8 
} 
 
struct Tentacle { 
    poison: u8, 
    owner: Alien 
} 
 
fn main() { 
let dhark = Alien { name: "Dharkalen".to_string(), n_tentacles: 7 }; 
 
    // defining dhark's tentacles: 
    for i in 0u8..dhark.n_tentacles { 
        Tentacle { poison: i * 3, owner: dhark }; // <- error! 
    } 
} 

The compiler gives a following error for the line in the for loop:

    error: use of moved value 'dhark' - move occurs because `dhark` has type `Alien`, which does not implement the `Copy` trait  

Each Alien Tentacle when it is defined seemingly tries to make a copy of the Alien instance as its owner, which would make no sense and is not allowed.

The correct version defines the owner in the Tentacle struct to have the type Rc<Alien>:

// see code in Chapter 7/code/refcount.rs  
use std::rc::Rc; 
 
#[derive(Debug)] 
struct Alien { 
    name: String, 
    n_tentacles: u8 
} 
 
#[derive(Debug)] 
struct Tentacle { 
    poison: u8, 
    owner: Rc<Alien> 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    let dhark = Alien { name: "Dharkalen".to_string(), n_tentacles: 7 }; 
 
    let dhark_master = Rc::new(dhark); 
 
    for i in 0u8..dhark_master.n_tentacles { 
        let t = Tentacle { poison: i * 3, owner: dhark_master.clone() }; 
       println!("{:?}", t); 
    } 
} 

This prints the following output:

Tentacle {poison: 0, owner: Alien{name: "Dharkalen", n_tentacles: 7}}
Tentacle {poison: 3, owner: Alien{name: "Dharkalen", n_tentacles: 7}}
Tentacle {poison: 6, owner: Alien{name: "Dharkalen", n_tentacles: 7 }}
Tentacle {poison: 18, owner: Alien{name: "Dharkalen", n_tentacles: 7}}

We envelop our Alien instance in an Rc<T> type with Rc::new(dhark). Applying the clone() method on this Rc object provides each Tentacle with its own reference to the Alien object. Note that clone() here copies the Rc pointer, not the Alien struct. We also annotate the structs with #[derive(Debug)], so that we can print out their instances through a println!("{:?}", t);.

If we want mutability inside our Rc type, we have to use either a Cell pointer if the value implements the Copy trait, or a RefCell pointer otherwise. Both these smart pointers are found in the std:cell module.

The Rc pointer type can however only be used inside one thread of execution only. If you need shared ownership across multiple threads, you need to use the Arc&lt;T> pointer (atomic reference counted box), which is the thread-safe counterpart of Rc (see Chapter 9</span>, Concurrency - Coding for Multicore Execution in the section Atomic reference counting).

About the Reviewer

Tom Verbesselt started his career as a software engineer in the amazing early world of 3D scanning and printing. However, he couldn't ignore his passion for teaching, and so he became a lecturer at the graduate program at CVO Antwerpen (Antwerp, Belgium). He started his own IT consultancy firm in 2003 and cofounded OWIC, a non-profit organization dedicated to teaching open source software tools, in 2016. Currently, he is the head of the graduate program in IT at CVO Antwerpen, and he is passionate about mobile, web, and new technology.

I have known Ivo for more than 10 years as a colleague at CVO Antwerpen. He is a born teacher and always willing to share his knowledge and insights. He is passionate about programming, and this book will give you all that you need to get started in Rust.
This book is a well guided tour around the Rust programming language. I was amazed by the speed, elegance, and possibilities of this programming language. After reading this book, you will have a solid foundation in the language and the advantages and possibilities that it offers. I've loved every page of it, and I hope you will do too.

OS and embedded system development

Several open source operating systems are written in Rust. Most of them are only proofs of concept, or suitable as demos in courses on operating systems. The only system that goes a step further is redox (see https://www.redox-os.org), which is actively being developed. It has a microkernel architecture and comes with a window manager, as well as basic applications such as an editor and file manager. You can find a comparison of several Rust OS projects, as well as a great number of useful links on this site https://github.com/flosse/rust-os-comparison.

tock (https://www.tockos.org) is an embedded operating system written in Rust and designed for running multiple concurrent, mutually distrustful applications on low-memory and low-power microcontrollers.

cortex_m_rtfm is a bare metal concurrency framework for Cortex-M microcontrollers geared towards robotics and control systems. zinc (http://zinc.rs/) is an example of a project that uses Rust to write a code stack for processors (currently ARM).

If you need async I/O in your project, look at tokio (https://tokio.rs) and the many related crates. At the core of tokio is the futures crate to model asynchronous computations. Read https://lukesteensen.com/2016/12/getting-started-with-tokio/ to get you started.

Furthermore, crates exist for a lot of other categories, such as functional and embedded programming (see http://spin.atomicobject.com/2015/02/20/rust-language-c-embedded/), data structures, image processing (the image crate), audio, compression, encoding and encryption (such as rust-crypto and crypto), regular expressions, parsing, hashing, tooling, testing, template engines, and so on.

Have a look at crates.io or the Awesome Rust compilation (see https://github.com/rust-unofficial/awesome-rust) to get an idea of what is available.

Some other examples

In the following macro, massert, we mimic the behavior of the assert! macro, which does nothing when its expression argument is true, but panics when it is false:

macro_rules! massert { 
    ($arg:expr) => ( 
            if $arg {} 
            else { panic!("Assertion failed!"); } 
    ); 
} 

For example: massert!(1 == 42); will print out:

thread '<main>' panicked at 'Assertion failed!'  

In the following statements, we test whether vector v contains certain elements:

    let v = [10, 40, 30]; 
    massert!(v.contains(&30)); 
    massert!(!v.contains(&50)); 

The macro unless mimics an unless statement, where a branch is executed if the arg condition is not true. For example:

unless!(v.contains(&25), println!("v does not contain 25")); 

It should print out:

v does not contain 25  

Because the condition is not true. This is also a one-line macro:

macro_rules! unless { 
    ($arg:expr, $branch:expr) => ( if !$arg { $branch }; ); 
} 

The last example combines the techniques we have seen so far. In Chapter 3, Using Functions and Control Structures, in the Attributes - testing section, we saw how to make a test function with the #[test] attribute. Let us create a macro, test_eq, that when invoked with test_eq!(seven_times_six_is_forty_two, 7 * 6, 42); generates a test function:

        #[test] 
        fn seven_times_six_is_forty_two() { 
            assert_eq!(7 * 6, 42); 
        } 

We also want a test that fails:

test_eq!(seven_times_six_is_not_forty_three, 7 * 6, 43); 

The first argument to test_eq is the test's name, and the second and third arguments are values to be compared for equality, so in general test_eq!(name, left, right);.

Here, name is an identifier; left and right are expressions. Like the create_fn invocation previously, the test_eq! calls are written outside any function.

Now we can compose our macro as follows:

macro_rules! test_eq { 
    ($name:ident, $left:expr, $right:expr) => { 
        #[test] 
        fn $name() { 
            assert_eq!($left, $right); 
        } 
    } 
} 

Create the test runner by calling rustc --test macros.rs.

When the macros executable is run, it prints out this:

    running 2 tests
    test seven_times_six_is_forty_two ... ok
    test seven_times_six_is_not_forty_three ... FAILED  

A macro can also be recursive, calling itself in the expansion branch. This is useful for processing tree-structured input, like when parsing HTML code.

The compiler can show us the expanded macro. Let us say we want to compile main.rs which contains some macro(s). Call rustc with the following options to show the expanded output (you will have to use the nightly compiler version here):

rustc main.rs --pretty=expanded -Z unstable-options 

To debug a macro, and to give you more info about how your macro works, the macros log_syntax and trace_macros(true) can be used. Again, both macros are unstable features, so you must use them with a Rust compiler from the nightly branch and behind these feature gates:

#![feature(trace_macros)]  
#![feature(log_syntax)] 

For a complete example, see macro_debug.rs.

Creating threads

A thread can be created by spawning it; this creates an independent detached child thread that in general can outlive its parent. This is demonstrated in the following code snippet:

// code from Chapter 9/code/thread_spawn.rs:  
use std::thread; 
use std::time; 
 
fn main() { 
    thread::spawn(move || { 
 println!("Hello from the goblin in the spawned thread!"); 
    }); 
} 

The argument to spawn is a closure (here, without parameters, it is indicated as ||), which is scheduled to execute independently from the parent thread, which is shown here as main(). Notice that it is a moving closure which takes ownership of the variables in a given context. Our closure here is a simple print statement, but in a real situation this could be replaced by a heavy or time-consuming operation.

When we execute this code, we normally don't see any output. Why is this? It turns out that main() is a bad parent (as far as threading is concerned) and doesn't wait for its children to end properly. The output of the spawned thread only becomes visible if we let main() pause for a brief moment before terminating. This can be done with the thread::sleep method,which takes the Duration, a type defined in the std::time module:

   fn main() { 
    thread::spawn(move || { ...  }); 
    thread::sleep(time::Duration::from_millis(50)); 
} 

This prints out the following:

Hello from the goblin in the spawned thread!.  

In general, this pause period is not needed. Child threads that are spawned can live longer than their parent threads, and will continue to execute when their parents have already stopped.

Better practice in this case, however, is to capture the handle join that spawn returns in a variable. Calling the join() method on handle will block the parent thread, making it wait until the child thread is finished. This returns a Result instance. unwrap() will take the value from Ok, returning the result of the child thread, which is () in this case because it is a print statement, or panic in the Err case:

fn main() { 
    let handle = thread::spawn(move || { 
        println!("Hello from the goblin in the spawned thread!"); 
    }); 
// do other work in the meantime 
   let output = handle.join().unwrap(); // wait for child thread 
   println!("{:?}", output); // () 
} 

If no other work has to be done while the child thread is executing, we can also write this:

thread::spawn(move || {  
// work done in child thread  
}).join(); 

In this case, we are waiting synchronously for the child thread to finish, so there is no good reason to start a new thread.

Why do we need a moving closure when spawning a thread? Examine the following code, which does not compile:

// code from Chapter 9/code/moving_closure.rs:   
use std::thread; 
 
fn main() { 
      read(); 
} 
 
fn read() { 
    let book = read_book("book1.txt"); 
    thread::spawn(|| { 
        println!("{:?}", book); 
    }); 
} 
fn read_book(s: &str) { } 

This gives us error: closure may outlive the current function, but it borrows `book`, which is owned by the current function. Indeed, the closure may be run by the spawned thread long after the read() function has terminated, as it has freed the memory of book. But if we make it a moving closure, which takes ownership of its environment, the code compiles:

thread::spawn(move|| { 
        println!("{:?}", book); 
   }); 

Arrays, vectors, and slices

Suppose we have a bunch of alien creatures to populate a game level, then we probably want to store their names in a handy list. Rust's array is just what we need:

// from Chapter 4/code/arrays.rs 
let aliens = ["Cherfer", "Fynock", "Shirack", "Zuxu"]; 
println!("{:?}", aliens); 

To make an array, separate the different items by commas and surround the whole with [ ] (rectangular brackets). All items must be of the same type. Such an array is of fixed size (it must be known at compile time) and cannot be changed; it is stored in one contiguous piece of memory in stack memory.

If the items have to be modifiable, declare your array with let mut; however even then the number of items cannot change:

let mut aliens = ["Cherfer", "Fynock", "Shirack", "Zuxu"]; 

The array aliens could be type annotated as [&str; 4], where the first parameter is the type of the items, and the second is their number.

let aliens: [&str; 4] = ["Cherfer", "Fynock", "Shirack", "Zuxu"]; 

If we want to initialize an array with three Zuxus, that's easy too:

let zuxus = ["Zuxu"; 3]; 

How would you make an empty array? Like this:

let mut empty: [i32; 0] = []; 
println!("{:?}", empty); // [] 

We can access individual items with their index, starting from 0:

println!("The first item is: {}", aliens[0]); // Cherfer 
println!("The third item is: {}", aliens[2]); // Shirack 

The number of items in the array is given by aliens.len(), so how would you get the last item?

Using the following statement:

aliens[aliens.len() - 1] 

Alternatively, this can be found with the following statement:

aliens.iter().last().unwrap(); 

What do you think will happen when we try to change an item, like this?

aliens[2] = "Facehugger"; 

Hopefully you didn't think that Rust would allow this, did you? Unless you told it explicitly that aliens can change with the following statement:

let mut aliens = [...]; 

In many cases the compiler checks whether the array index stays within the array bounds.

The index is also checked at runtime to be within the array bounds 0 and aliens.len(); if it is not, the program crashes with a runtime error or panic:

println!("This item does not exist: {}", aliens[10]); 

This gives the following output:

thread '<main>' panicked at 'index out of bounds: the len is 4 but the index is 10'  

Pointers to arrays use automatic dereferencing so that you do not need to use * explicitly, as demonstrated in this code snippet:

let pa = &aliens; 
println!("Third item via pointer: {}", pa[2]); 

This prints the following output:

Third item via pointer: Shirack

If we want to go through the items successively one by one, and print them out or do something useful with them, we can do it like this:

for ix in 0..aliens.len() { 
    println!("Alien no {} is {}", ix, aliens[ix]); 
} 

This works and it gives us for each item its index, which might be useful. But we use the index to fetch each consecutive item, and each time Rust has to check whether we are still within the bounds of the array in memory. That's why it is not very efficient, and in the section Iterators in Chapter 6, Using Traits and OOP in Rust, we will see a much more efficient way by iterating over the items:

for a in aliens.iter() {    
    println!("The next alien is {}", a); 
} 

The for loop can be written even shorter as:

for a in &aliens  { ... } 

Looping

For repeating pieces of code, Rust has the common while loop, again without parentheses around the condition:

// from Chapter 3/code/loops.rs 
fn main() { 
  let max_power = 10; 
  let mut power = 1; 
    while power < max_power { 
        print!("{} ", power); // prints without newline 
        power += 1;           // increment counter 
    } 
} 

This prints the following output:

    1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

To start an infinite loop, use the loop statement, as shown below:

loop { 
        power += 1; 
        if power == 42 { 
            // Skip the rest of this iteration 
        continue; 
        } 
        print!("{}  ", power); 
        if power == 50 { 
           print!("OK, that's enough for today"); 
        break;  // exit the loop 
        } 
} 

All the power values including 50 but except 42 are printed; then the loop stops with the statement break. The value 42 is not printed because of the continue statement. So, loop is equivalent to a while true and a loop with a conditioned break simulates a do while in other languages.

When loops are nested inside each other, the break and continue statements apply to the immediate enclosing loop. Any loop statement (also the while and for loop which we'll see next) can be preceded by a label (denoted as labelname:) to allow us to jump to the next or outer enclosing loop, as in this snippet:

  'outer: loop { 
        println!("Entered the outer dungeon."); 
        inner: loop { 
            println!("Entered the inner dungeon."); 
            // break;    // this would break out of the inner loop 
            break 'outer; // breaks to the outer loop 
        } 
        println!("This treasure can sadly never be reached."); 
    } 
    println!("Exited the outer dungeon!"); 

This prints the following output:

    Entered the outer dungeon.
    Entered the inner dungeon.
    Exited the outer dungeon!

Obviously, the use of labels makes reading the code more difficult, so use it wisely. The infamous goto statement from C luckily does not exist in Rust!

Looping where a variable var begins from a start value a to an end value b (exclusive) is done with a for loop over a range expression, as shown in the following statement:

for var in a..b 

Here is an example which prints the squares of the numbers 1 to 10:

for n in 1..11 { 
      println!("The square of {} is {}", n, n * n); 
} 

In general, for in loops over an iterator, which is an object that gives back a series of values one by one. The range a..b is the simplest form of iterator.

Each subsequent value is bound to the variable n and used in the next loop iteration. The for loop ends when there are no more values and the variable n then goes out of scope. If we don't need the value of the variable n in the loop, we can replace it with an _ (underscore), like this:

for _ in 1..11 { } 

The many bugs in C-style for loops, like the off-by-one error with the counter, cannot occur here, because we loop over an iterator.

Variables can also be used in a range, like in the following snippet which prints nine dots:

let mut x = 10; 
for _ in 1..x { x -= 1; print!("."); } 

We'll examine iterators in more detail in Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling.

Values and primitive types

Constants that have been initialized have a value. Values exist in different types: 70 is an integer, 3.14 is a float, and Z and θ are the type of a character. Characters are Unicode values that take four bytes of memory each. Godzilla is a string of type &str (which is Unicode UTF8 by default), true and false are the type of Boolean values. Integers can be written in different formats:

Hexadecimal format with 0x, like 0x46 for 70.
Octal format with 0o, like 0o106 for 70.
Binary format with 0b, like 0b1000110.

Underscores can be used for readability, as in 1_000_000. Sometimes the compiler will urge you to indicate more explicitly the type of number with a suffix, for example (the number after u or i is the number of memory bits used, namely: 8, 16, 32, or 64).
The 10usize denotes an unsigned integer of machine word size (usize), which can be any of the following types: u8, u16, u32, u64.
The 10isize denotes a signed integer of machine word size (isize), which can be any of the following types: i8, i16, i32, i64
In the cases above on a 64-bit operating system usize is in fact u64, and isize is equivalent to i64.
The 3.14f32 denotes a 32-bit floating-point number.
The 3.14f64 denotes a 64-bit floating-point number.
The numeric types i32 and f64 are the defaults if no suffix is given, but in that case to differentiate between them you must end an f64 value with .0, like:

let e = 7.0; 

In general, indicating a specific type is recommended.

Rust is like any other C-like language when it comes to the different operators and their precedence. However, notice that Rust does not have increment (++) or decrement (--) operators. To compare two values for equality use == , and != to test if they are different.

There is even the empty value () of zero size, which is the only value of the so called unit type (). It is used to indicate the return value when an expression or a function returns nothing (no value), as is the case for a function that only prints to the console. () is not the equivalent of a null value in other languages; () is no value, whereas null is a value.

Interfacing with C

Because of the vast functionality that exists in C code, it can sometimes be useful to delegate processing to a C routine, instead of writing everything in Rust.

You can call all functions and types from the C standard library by using the libc crate, which must be obtained through Cargo.

You have to add the following to Cargo.toml:

 [dependencies] 
    libc = "*" 

If you use Rust's nightly version, this is not necessary, but you have to use a feature attribute (or a feature gate, as they are also called) at the start of your code:

    #![feature(libc)]

Feature gates are common in Rust to enable the use of a certain functionality, but they are not available in stable Rust, only in the current development branch (nightly release).

If you have both the stable and nightly versions installed, you can easily switch between them using the commands rustup default nightly and rustup default stable.

Then, simply add the following to your Rust code:

extern crate libc; 

To import C functions and types, you can sum them up like this:

use libc::{c_void, size_t, malloc, free}; 

You can also use the wildcard * to make them all available, like in use libc::*;.

To work with C (or another language) from Rust, you will have to use the Foreign Function Interface (FFI); its utilities are in the std::ffi module. A foreign function interface is a mechanism by which a program written in one programming language can call routines or make use of services written in another language. But do realize that FFI calls cause significant overhead, so use them only when it is worth it.

Here is a simple example of calling C to print out a Rust String with the C function puts:

// code from Chapter 10/code/calling_libc.rs: 
extern crate libc;
use libc::puts;
use std::ffi::CString; 
 
fn main() { 
   let sentence = "Merlin is the greatest magician!"; 
   let to_print = CString::new(sentence).unwrap();
   unsafe {
       puts(to_print.as_ptr());    } 
   } 

This prints out the sentence:

Merlin is the greatest magician!

The new() method of CString will produce a C-compatible string (ending with 0 bytes) from the Rust String. The as_ptr() method returns a pointer to this C string.

Expressions

Rust is an expression-oriented language, which means that most pieces of code are in fact expressions, that is, they compute a value and return that value. However, expressions on themselves do not form meaningful code; they must be used in statements.

let bindings like the following are declaration statements; they are not expressions:

// see Chapter 2/code/expressions.rs 
let a = 2;    // a binds to 2 
let b = 5;    // b binds to 5 
let n = a + b;   // n binds to 7 

But, here, a + b is an expression and, if we omit the semicolon at the end, the resulting value (here the value 7) is returned. This is often used when a function needs to return its value (see examples in the next chapter). Ending an expression with a semicolon like a + b; suppresses this behaviour, thus throwing away the return value and making it an expression statement returning the unit value ().

Code is usually a sequence of statements, one on each code line and Rust has to know when a statement ends, that's why nearly every Rust code line ends with a semicolon.

What do you think the assignment m = 42; is? It is not a binding, because there is no let binding (that should have happened on a previous code line). It is an expression that returns the unit value ().

A compound binding like let p = q = 3; is not allowed in Rust, it returns the following error:

error: unresolved name q

However, you can chain let bindings like this:

let mut n = 0; 
let mut m = 1; 
let t = m; m = n; n  = t; 
println!("{} {} {}", n, m, t); // 

This gives an output as: 1 0 1

Exercise:

Print out the values of a, b, and n after this code snippet. Explain the value of a(For an example code, seecompound_let.rs):

let mut a = 5;
let mut b = 6;
let n = 7;
let a = b = n;

A code block is also an expression, which returns the value of its last expression if we omit the semicolon. For example, in the following code snippet, n1 gets the value 7, but n2 gets no value (or, rather, the unit value ()), because the return value of the second block was suppressed:

let n1 = { 
let a = 2; 
let b = 5; 
a + b   // <-- no semicolon! 
}; 
  println!("n1 is: {}", n1);  // prints: n1 is 7 
  let n2 = { 
    let a = 2; 
    let b = 5; 
    a + b; 
  }; 
  println!("n2 is: {:?}", n2);  // prints: n2 is () 

The variables a and b are here declared in a code block and live only as long as the block itself, they are local to the block. Note that the semicolon after the closing brace of the block, };, is needed. To print out the unit value (), we need {:?} as format specifier.

The stability of Rust and its evolution

Rust started out with version 1.0.0, and, at the time of writing, the current version is 1.20.0. Version numbers follow the semantic versioning principle (see http://semver.org/ for further information):

Patch release: For bug fixes and other minor changes, increment the last number, for example 1.18.1
Minor release: For new features which don't break existing features, increment the middle number, for example 1.19.0
Major release: For changes which break backwards compatibility, increment the first number, for example 2.0.0

So, no breaking changes will occur during the current 1.n.m cycle versions, as this cycle is backward compatible; Rust projects which are developed in the older versions of this cycle will still compile in a more recent version. However, to be able to work with new features which are only contained in the more recent version, it is mandatory to compile your code to that specific version.

Rust has a very dynamic cycle of progression. Work is performed on three releases (called channels or builds simultaneously)--nightly, beta, and stable, and they follow a strict six-week release cycle like web browsers:

The stable channel is the current stable release, which is advocated for Rust projects that are being used in production.
The beta channel is where new features are deemed stable enough to be tested out in bigger, non-deployed projects.
The nightly channel build contains the latest experimental features; it is produced from the master branch every 24 hours. You would use it only for experimentation.

The beta and stable channel builds are only updated as new features are backported to their branch. With this arrangement, Rust allows users to access new features and bug fixes quickly.

Here is a concrete example: 1.18 was released on 18th June, 2017, the 1.19-beta was released at the same time, and the master development branch was advanced to 1.20. Six weeks later, on 30th July, Rust 1.19 will come out of beta and become a stable release, 1.20 will be promoted to 1.21-beta, and the master will become the eventual 1.21.

Some features in an experimental stage can only work when the code contains an attribute #[feature]. These may not be used on the stable release channel, only on a beta or nightly release; an example is the box syntax (see chapter 2\code\references.rs).

Iterators

An iterator is an object that returns the items of a collection in sequence, from the first to the last. To return the following item, it uses a next() method. Here, we have an opportunity to use an Option. Because an iterator can have no more values at the last next() call, next() always returns an Option, Some(value) when there is a value and None when there are no more values to return.

The simplest object that has this behavior is a range of numbers 0..n (remember n is excluded). Every time we used a for loop like for i in 0..n the underlying iterator mechanism was put to work. Let's see an example:

// see code in Chapter 5/code/iterators.rs 
let mut rng = 0..7; 
println!("> {:?}", rng.next()); // 
println!("> {:?}", rng.next()); // 
for n in rng { 
    print!("{} - ", n); 
} // prints 2 - 3 - 4 - 5 - 6 

This prints the following output:

    Some(0)
    Some(1)

We see here the function next() at work, producing 0 and 1, and so on; the for loop continues until the end.

Exercise:
In the previous example we saw that the function next() returns a Some type value, a variant of type Option (see the Result and Option section in Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns). Write an endless loop over the range rng with the function next() and see what happens. How would you break the endless loop? Use a match on the Option value (for an example, see Chapter 5/exercises/range_next.rs). In fact, the for loop we saw right before this exercise is syntactic sugar for this loop - match construct.

Iterators are also the preferred way to loop over arrays or slices. Let's revisit the aliens array from Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns:

let aliens = ["Cherfer", "Fynock", "Shirack", "Zuxu"];" 

Instead of using the index to show all the items one by one, let's do it the iterator way with the iter() function:

for alien in aliens.iter() { 
   print!("{} / ", alien) 
   // process alien 
} 

This prints out the following output:

    Cherfer / Fynock / Shirack / Zuxu /  

The alien variable is of type &str, a reference to each of the items in turn (technically, it is here of type &str, because the items themselves are of type &str, but this is not relevant to the point being made here). This is much more performant and safe than using an index, because now Rust doesn't need to do index-bounds checking, we're always certain to move within the memory of the array.

An even shorter way is to write the following:

for alien in &aliens { 
    print!("{} / ", alien) 
} 

The variable alien is also of type &str, but the print! macro automatically dereferences this. If you want them to print out in reverse order, do aliens.iter().rev(). Other iterators we encountered in the previous chapter, where the chars() and split() methods on Strings.

Iterators are lazy by nature, they do not generate values unless asked and we ask by calling the next() method or applying a for in loop. That makes sense, we don't want to allocate one million integers in the following binding:

let rng = 0..1000_000; // _ makes the number 1000000 more readable 

We want to allocate memory only when we need it.

Type checking and conversions

Rust has to know the type of variables, because that way it can check (at compile time) that they are only used in ways their type permits. That way programs are type safe and a whole range of bugs are avoided.

This also means that we cannot change the type of a variable during its lifetime, because of static typing, for example, the variable score in the following snippet cannot change from an integer to a string:

// see Chapter 2/code/type_errors.rs 
// warning: this code does not work! 
fn main() { 
let score: i32 = 100; 
score = "YOU WON!" 
} 

With this, we get the compiler error, as follows:

error: mismatched types: expected i32, found reference

However, I am allowed to write this as:

let score = "YOU WON!"; 

Rust lets me redefine variables; each let binding creates a new variable score that hides the previous one, which is freed from memory. This is actually quite useful because variables are immutable by default.

Adding strings with + (like the players in the following code) is not defined in Rust:

let player1 = "Rob"; 
let player2 = "Jane"; 
let player3 = player1 + player2; 

With this we get an error stating:

error: binary operation `+` cannot be applied to type `&str`

In Rust you can use the to_string() method to convert the value to a String type like this:

let player3 = player1.to_string() + player2; 

Alternatively, you could use the format! macro:

let player3 = format!("{}{}", player1, player2); 

In both cases, the variable player3 has the value RobJane.

Let's find out what happens when you assign a value from a variable of a certain type to another variable of a different type:

// see Chapter 2/code/type_conversions.rs 
fn main() { 
  let points = 10i32; 
  let mut saved_points: u32 = 0; 
   saved_points = points; // error ! 
} 

This is again not allowed, therefore, we get the same error, as follows:

error: mismatched types: expected u32, found i32

To enable maximal type checking Rust does not permit automatic (or implicit) conversions of one type to another like C++ does, thus avoiding a lot of hard-to-find bugs. For example, the numbers after the decimal point are lost when converting an f32 value to an i32 value; this could lead to errors when done automatically.

We can however do an explicit conversion (also called a casting) with the keyword as follows:

saved_points = points as u32; 

When the variable points contains a negative value, the sign would be lost after conversion. Similarly, when casting from a wider value like a float to an integer, the decimal part is truncated. See the following example:

  let f2 = 3.14; 
  saved_points = f2 as u32; // truncation to value 3 occurs here 

Also, the value must be convertible to the new type, a string cannot be converted to an integer, for example:

  let mag = "Gandalf"; 
   saved_points = mag as u32; // 

This gives an error, as follows:

error: non-scalar cast:`&str`as`u32`

Built-in traits and operator overloading

The Rust standard library is packed with traits, which are used all over the place. For example, there are traits for which the compiler is capable of providing a basic implementation with a #[derive] attribute, as we saw in the section on Traits:

Comparing instances: The Eq and PartialEq trait
Ordering instances: The Ord and PartialOrd trait
Creating an empty instance: The Default trait
To create a zero instance of a numeric data type: The Zero trait

The next chapter shows an example of how to implement the following three traits:

Formatting a value using {:?}: The Debug trait, defining an fmt method
Copy an instance: The Copy trait
Create a duplicate instance: The Clone trait
Computing a hash: The Hash trait
Adding instances: The Add trait, defining an add method. The + operator is just a nice way to use add: n + m is the same as n.add(m). So if we implement the Add trait, we can use the + operator, this is called operator overloading.

The Add trait has the following signature:

      pub trait Add<RHS = Self> { 
           type Output; 
  
            fn add(self, rhs: RHS) -> Self::Output; 
      }

So the add method and the trait item Output must both be implemented. The code impl_add.rs shows an implementation of the Add trait:

struct AType { 
    value: i32, 
} 
 
impl AType { 
    fn new(value: i32) -> AType { 
        AType { value: value } 
    } 
} 
 
impl Add for AType { 
    type Output = AType; 
 
    fn add(self, other: AType) -> AType { 
        AType { value: self.value + other.value } 
    } 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    let at1 = AType{ value: 7 }; 
    let at2 = AType{ value: 42 }; 
    let at3 = at1.add(at2); 
    println!("{:?}", at3); 
    let at4 = AType{ value: 2 }; 
    let at5 = AType{ value: 108 }; 
    let at6 = at4 + at5; 
    println!("{:?}", at6); 
} 

This prints the following output:

    AType { value: 49 }
    AType { value: 110 }  

Note that we can use it as a + operator or an add method. A lot of other traits can also be used to overload operators, such as Sub(-), Mul(*), Deref (*v), Index([]), and so on.

Freeing resources of an object (when it goes out of scope): The Drop trait, in other words the object has a destructor. Freeing resources is taken care of automatically by the compiler, but by implementing Drop you can do additional things.

In the section Iterators we described how an iterator works and used it on ranges and arrays. In fact an iterator is also defined as a trait in Rust in std::iter::Iterator. From the docs for iterator (see http://doc.rust-lang.org/std/iter/trait.Iterator.html) we see that we only need to define the next() method, which advances the iterator to return the next value as an Option type. When the next() method is implemented for the type of your object, we can then use a for in loop to iterate over the object.

Pointers

The variable n in the binding let n = 42i32; is stored on the stack. Values on the stack or on the heap can be accessed by pointers. A pointer is a variable that contains the memory address of some value. To access the value it points to, dereference the pointer with *. This happens automatically in simple cases like in println! macro or when a pointer is given as a parameter to a method. For example in the following code m is a pointer containing the address of n:

// see code in Chapter 7/code/references.rs: 
let m = &n; 
println!("The address of n is {:p}", m); 
println!("The value of n is {}", *m); 
println!("The value of n is {}", m); 

The preceding code prints out the following output. The address of the variable n differs with each program run:

    The address of n is 0x7078eff8bc
    The value of n is 42
    The value of n is 42  

Why do we need pointers? When we work with dynamically allocated values that can change in size like a string, the memory address of that value is not known at compile time. Because of this, the memory address needs to be calculated at runtime. So to be able to keep track of it, we need a pointer to it, whose value changes when the string's location in memory changes.

The compiler automatically takes care of the memory allocation of pointers, and the freeing up of memory when their lifetime ends. You don't have to do this yourself like in C/C++, where you could screw up by freeing at the wrong moment, or freeing memory multiple times.

This incorrect use of pointers in languages like C++ leads to all kinds of problems.

However, Rust enforces a strong set of rules at compile time called the borrow checker, so we are protected against them. We have already seen them in action, but from here onwards we'll explain the logic behind its rules.

Pointers can also be passed as arguments to functions, and can be returned from functions, but the compiler severely restricts their usage.

When passing a pointer value to a function, it is always better to use the reference-dereference &* mechanism, like in this example:

let q = &42; 
   println!("{}", square(q)); // 1764 
 
fn square(k: &i32) -> i32 { 
    *k * *k 
}

This prints out the following output:

The square is: 1764

Rust has many kinds of pointers, which we will explore in this chapter. All pointers (except raw pointers, discussed in Chapter 10, Programming at the Boundaries) are guaranteed to be non-null (that is, they point to a valid location in memory) and are automatically cleaned up.

Inlining assembly code

In Rust, we can embed assembly code. This should be extremely rare, but one can imagine situations where this might be useful, for example, when you require utmost performance or very low-level control. But of course, the portability of your code and perhaps its stability decrease when doing this. The Rust compiler will probably generate better assembly code than you would write, so it isn't worth the effort most of the time.

The mechanism works by using the asm! macro, as in this example, where we calculate a - b in the subtract function by calling the assembly code:

// code from Chapter 10/code/asm.rs: 
#![feature(asm)] 
 
fn subtract(a: i32, b: i32) -> i32 { 
    let sub: i32; 
    unsafe { 
        asm!("sub $2, $1; mov $1, $0" : "=r"(sub) : "r"(a), "r"(b) 
); 
    } 
    sub 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    println!("{}", subtract(42, 7))  

This prints out the result 35.

asm! can only be used with the feature gate #![feature(asm)].

asm! has a number of parameters separated by :. The first is the assembly template, containing the assembly code as a string, then come the output and input operands.

You can indicate the kind of processors your assembly code is meant to execute on with the cfg attribute and its value, target_arch, for example:

#[cfg(any(target_arch = "x86", target_arch = "x86_64"))] 

The compiler will then check whether you have specified valid assembly code for that processor.

This feature is not yet enabled in Rust 1.21 on the stable release channel. To use this mechanism (or other unstable features) in the meantime, you have to use Rust from the master branch (which is the nightly release). Install that version and change to it with the command rustup default nightly.

OOP in Rust

While there is no unique definition of what object-orientation in a programming language is, it is clear by now that in Rust you can express several important OO-concepts.

Objects with data (their state) and methods (their behavior):

Rust has these--structs (and other types such as enums) have data and impl blocks provide methods on them. The definitions of structure and behavior are separate.

Encapsulation of data and implementation:

In other words--external code can only change or interact with an object through its public methods. In Rust by default everything is private, so not accessible from the outside. You can decide which types, functions, methods and modules are public by adding a pub keyword before their definition. For more detail, see Chapter 8, Organizing Code and Macros in the section, Visibility of items.

Inheritance to promote code reuse and use polymorphism:

In Rust, inheritance, strictly speaking, does not exist: a struct cannot inherit its fields or methods from another struct. But the implementation of traits by structs can almost provide the same benefits. Indeed traits can inherit from other traits; see the next section Inheritance with traits.

Code reuse among structs can be obtained by letting them implement the same trait(s), because then they share the methods with default code from these trait(s). Polymorphism means objects of a different type can be treated as of one type, because they inherit from the same supertype or implement the same interface. As we saw in the section on Static and Dynamic Dispatch, Rust has trait objects to work with values of any type, as long as these values implement a particular trait.

We can conclude that, although the concept of a class and inheritance between classes is not present in Rust, nevertheless Rust enables the most important object-oriented concepts, more than in many other languages.

Boxes

Another pointer type in Rust is called the boxed pointer Box<T>, which can be defined for a value of a generic type T. A box is a non-copyable value. This pointer type is used to allocate objects on the heap.

For example, here we allocate an Alien value on the heap with: 
// see code in Chapter 7/code/boxes1.rs    
let mut a1 = Box::new(Alien{ planet: "Mars".to_string(), n_tentacles: 4 }); 
println!("{}", a1.n_tentacles); // 4 

The mutable variable a1 is the only owner of this memory resource that may read from and write to it.

We can make a reference to the value pointed to by the box pointer, and if both the original box and this new reference are mutable, we can change the object through this reference:

let a2 = &mut a1; 
println!("{}", a2.planet ); // Mars 
a2.n_tentacles = 5; 

After such a borrow the usual ownership rules as above hold: a1 no longer has access, not even for reading:

// error: cannot borrow `a1.n_tentacles` as immutable because `a1` is also borrowed as mutable 
println!("{}", a1.n_tentacles); // is error! 
// error: cannot assign to `a1.planet` because it is borrowed 
a1.planet = "Pluto".to_string();  // is error! 

We can also use this mechanism to put simple values on the heap, like this:

let n = Box::new(42); 

As always n points by default to an immutable value, and any attempt to change this with:

*n = 67; 

Provokes the following error:

    error: cannot assign to immutable `Box` content `*n`.  

As usual we dereference a Box with *:

let p = *n; 
println!("{}", p); // 42 

Another reference can also point to the dereferenced Box value:

let q = &*n; 
println!("{}", q); // 42

In the following example we see again a boxed value pointed to by n, but now the ownership of the value is given to a mutable pointer m:

// see code in Chapter 7/code/boxes2.rs    
let n = Box::new(42); 
let mut m = n; 
*m = 67; 
// println!("{}", n); // error: use of moved value: `n` 
println!("{}", m); // 67 

By dereferencing the m variable and assigning a new value, this value is entered into the memory location originally pointed to by the variable n. Of course the n variable cannot be used anymore, we get the following error:

    error: use of moved value: `n`  

Because the variable n is no longer the owner of the value.

Here is another example where the ownership clearly has moved from a1 to a2: 
let mut a1 = Box::new(Alien{ planet: "Mars".to_string(), n_tentacles: 4 }); 
   let a2 = a1; 
   println!("{}", a2.n_tentacles); // 4 

There is no data being copied here, only the address of the struct value. After the move a1 can no longer be used to access the data, the variable a2 is responsible for freeing the memory.

If a2 is given as argument to a function like use_alien below, a2 in its turn gives up the ownership, which is transferred to the function:

   use_alien(a2); 
   // Following line gives the error: use of moved value: `a2.n_tentacles` 
   // println!("{}", a2.n_tentacles);  
} // end of main() function 
 
fn use_alien(a: Box<Alien>) { 
    println!("An alien from planet {} is freed after the closing brace.", a.planet); 
} 

This prints out the following output:

    An alien from planet Mars is freed after the closing brace.  

Indeed when the use_alien() function is finished executing, the memory allocation for that value is freed.

In general let your function always take a simple reference as parameter (as in the square function mentioned earlier in section Pointers), rather than a parameter of the Box type. We could improve our example by calling a function use_alien2 as follows:

fn use_alien2(a: &Alien) { 
   println!("An alien from planet {} is freed", a.planet); 
} 

And calling it like this:

use_alien2(&*a2); 

Boxes also allow for automatic dereferencing, as in this following code snippet:

let ua = Box::new([1, 2, 3]); 
println!("{}", ua[0]); 

Which prints the following output:

1 

Sometimes your program needs to manipulate a recursive data structure that refers to itself, like the following struct

struct Recurs { 
    list: Vec<u8>, 
    rec_list: Option<Box<Recurs>> 
} 

In the codefile linked_list.rs, you can find a working example of a recursive linked list datastructure:

enum List { 
    Cons(u32, Box<List>), 
    Nil, 
} 

A linked list node List can take on any of these two variants:

Cons: Which is a tuple struct that wraps an element of type u32 and a Box pointer to the next node
Nil: Which is a node that signifies the end of the linked list

Especially note the 2 recursive methods like len and stringify. 

This represents a list of lists of bytes. The rec_list variable is either a Some<Box<Recurs>> containing a Box pointer to another list, or a None value which means the list of lists ends there. Because the number of items in this list (and thus its size) is only known at runtime, such structures always must be constructed as a Box type.

For other use-cases, prefer references over Boxes.

Why macros?

Macros make powerful language or syntax extensions, and thus metaprogramming, possible; for example, Rust has a regex! macro which allows for defining regular expressions in your program, which are compiled while your code is compiled. That way the regular expressions are verified and can be optimized at compile time, and so avoid runtime overhead.

Macros can capture repetitive or similar code patterns and replace them with other source code; the macro expands the original code into new code. This expansion happens early in compilation, before any static checking is done, so the resulting code is compiled together with the original code. In this sense, they much more resemble Lisp macros than C macros. Rust macros allow writing Don't Repeat Yourself ;(DRY) code, by factoring out the common parts of functions. But a macro is higher-level than a function, because a macro allows for generating the code for many functions at compile time.

So, as a Rust developer, you can also write your own macros, replacing repetitive code with much simpler code and thereby automating tasks. On the other side of the spectrum, this could even make it possible to write domain-specific languages. Macro coding follows a specific set of declarative pattern-based rules. Rust's macro system is also hygienic, which means no conflict is possible between variables used in the macro and variables outside the macro. Each macro expansion happens in a distinct syntax context, and each variable is tagged with the syntax context where it was introduced.

Macro code itself is harder to understand than normal Rust code, so it is not that easy to make. But on the other hand, you won't code macros every day; if a macro is tested, just use it. The full story of macro writing extends into advanced regions of Rust, but in the following sections we discuss the basic techniques for developing macros.

Importing external crates

In Chapter 6, Using Traits and OOP in Rust, in the Traits section, we developed in traits.rs structs for Alien, Zombie, and Predator characters that implemented a trait, Monster. The code file contained a main() function to make it executable. We will now incorporate this code (without the main() part) in a library project called monsters, and see how we can call this code.

Create the library project with cargo new monsters, creating a folder structure and a monsters/src/lib.rs file with template code:

#[test] 
fn it_works() { 
} 

Remove this code and replace it with the code from Chapter 6/code/traits.rs, but omit the main() function. We also add a simple print_from_monsters() function to test calling it from the library:

// from Chapter 8/code/monsters/src/lib.rs: 
fn print_from_monsters() { 
    println!("Printing from crate monsters!"); 
} 

Then compile the library with cargo build, producing a library file, libmonsters.rlib, in the target/debug folder.

Now we create a main.rs in the src folder, to make an executable that can call into our monsters library, and copy the original main() code from traits.rs into it, adding a call to print_from_monsters():

// from Chapter 8/code/monsters/src/main.rs: 
fn main() { 
    print_from_monsters(); 
    let zmb1 = Zombie {health: 75, damage: 15}; 
    println!("Oh no, I hear: {}", zmb1.noise()); 
    zmb1.attack(); 
    println!("{:?}", zmb1); 
} 

This is a common design pattern: a library project containing an executable program that can be used to demonstrate or test the library.

cargo build will now compile both projects if there are no problems.

However, the code does not yet compile, and the compiler says error: unresolved name `print_from_monsters`; clearly the code for the function is not found.

The first thing we have to do is make the library code available to our main program, which is done with the following statement placed at the start:

extern crate monsters; 

This statement will import all the (public) items contained in the monsters crate under a module with the same name. But this is not enough; we must also indicate that the print_from_monsters function is to be found in the module monsters. Indeed, the monsters crate creates an implicit module with the same name. So, we have to call our function as follows:

monsters::print_from_monsters(); 

Now we get error: function `print_from_monsters` is private, which tells us that the function is found, but is inaccessible in the library crate. This is easy; in the Visibility of items section we have seen how to remedy this: we prefix the function header with pub, like this:

pub fn print_from_monsters() { ... } 

Now this part of our code works! Open a terminal, go (cd) to the target/debug folder, and start the monsters executable. This prints out the following:

Printing from crate monsters!  

You will see that extern crate abc (with abc being a crate name) is often used in code, but you will never see extern crate std; why is this? The reason is that std is imported by default in every other crate. For the same reason, the contents of the prelude module are imported by default in every module.

Branching on a condition

Branching on a condition is done with a common if, if else, or if else if else construct, as in this example:

// from Chapter 3/code/ifelse.rs 
fn main() { 
  let dead = false; 
  let health = 48; 
  if dead { 
    println!("Game over!"); 
       return; 
  } 
  if dead { 
    println!("Game over!"); 
    return; 
  } else { 
    println!("You still have a chance to win!"); 
  } 
  if health >= 50 { 
      println!("Continue to fight!"); 
  } else if health >= 20  { 
      println!("Stop the battle and gain strength!"); 
  } else { 
      println!("Hide and try to recover!"); 
  } 
} 

This gives the following output:

    You still have a chance to win!
    Stop the battle and gain strength!

The condition after the if statement has to be a Boolean. However, unlike in C, the condition must not be enclosed in parentheses. Code blocks surrounded by { } (curly braces) are needed after the if, else, or else if statement. The first example also shows that we can get out of a function with the return value.

Also the if else condition is an expression that returns a value. This value can be used as a function call parameter in a print! statement, or it can be assigned in a let binding, like this:

let active = if health >= 50 { 
           true 
         }else{ 
           false 
         }; 
println!("Am I active? {}", active); 

This prints the following output:

    Am I active? false

The code blocks could contain many lines, but be careful: when returning a value, you must omit the; (semi-colon) after the last expression in the if or else block (see section Expressions in Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types). Moreover, all branches always must return a value of the same type.

This also alleviates the need for a ternary operator (?: ), like in C++; simply use if, as follows:

let adult = true; 
let age = if adult { "+18" } else { "-18" }; 
println!("Age is {}", age);  // 

This gives the following output:

    Age is +18

Exercise:

See code in Chapter 3/exercises/iftest.rs.
Try adding a; (semi-colon) after the +18 and -18 values, like this {"+18";}, what value will be printed for the variable age? What happens if you type annotate the variable age as &str?
See if you can omit the { } (curly braces) if there is only one statement in the block.
Also, verify if this code is OK:
let health = -3;
let result = if health <=0 { "Game over man!" };

How would you correct this statement if necessary?--by using pattern matching, which we will examine in the next chapter, also branches code, but does so based on the value of a variable.

Getting input from the console

Suppose we want to capture the nickname of our player(s) before starting the game, how would we do that? Input or output functionality is handled by the module io in the crate std. It has a function stdin() to read input from the console. This function returns an object of type Stdin, which is a handle to the input stream. The object Stdin has a method read_line(buf) to read a full line of input, that ends with a new line character (that is, when the user hits Enter). This input is read into a String buffer buf. A method is a name for a function defined for a certain type, and it is called using dot notation, like object.method (see Chapter 6, ;Using Traits and OOP in Rust).

So our code will look like this:

let mut buf = String::new(); 
io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf); 

But that is not good enough for Rust, it gives us the following warning:

    warning: unused result which must be used  

Rust is foremost a safe language and we must be ready to cope with everything than can occur. Reading a line might work if an input value is given. But it can also fail, for example, if this code was running in a background job on a machine, so that no console is available to get input from.

How to cope with that? Well, the function read_line() returns a value Result, that can either be a real value (an Ok), when everything works fine, or an error value (an Err), when there is a problem. To cope with a possible error, we need an ok() and an expect() function. The function ok() converts the value Result into a value Option (which contains how many bytes were read), the function expect() gives that value, or shows its message when an error occurs. In Rust a program panics when an error occurs that cannot be recovered from, and the string argument from the function expect() is displayed to tell us where it occurs.

This is written in Rust in a chained form (a bit unusual the first time you see it) as follows:

    io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf).ok().expect("Error!");  

Rust allows us to write these successive calls on separate lines, which for most people clarifies the code a lot:

// from Chapter 4/code/input.rs 
use std::io; 
 
fn main() { 
   println!("What's your name, noble warrior?"); 
   let mut buf = String::new(); 
   io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf) 
              .ok() 
              .expect("Failed to read line"); 
   println!("{}, that's a mighty name indeed!", buf); 
} 

When running this code from the command line we get the following conversation:

    What's your name, noble warrior?
    Riddick
    Riddick
    that's a mighty name indeed!  

Can you guess why that's a mighty name indeed! appears on a new line? Indeed, the input buf still contains a newline character \n! Luckily we have a method trim() to remove trailing and leading whitespace from a string. If we insert the line:

let name = buf.trim(); 
println!("{}, that's a mighty name indeed!", name); 

We now get a correct output, like the following:

    Riddick, that's a mighty name indeed! 

In case the input does not succeed, our program crashes with the following output:

    What's your name, noble warrior?
    thread '<main>' panicked at 'Failed to read line'  

Instead of using this chained .ok().expect() form, you can also use a shorter form with a function unwrap() like this:

io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf).unwrap(); 

This unwraps a value Result, yielding the content of a value Ok (or of a value Some in the case of a value Option), but panics if the value is an Err (or a None for Option), with a panic message provided by the Err's value.

Another alternative is to test with the function is_ok(), which returns true if the result is Ok:

if io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf).is_ok() { 
    let name = buf.trim(); 
    println!("{}, that's a mighty name indeed!", name); 
} 
else { 
    println!("Failed to read line!"); 
} 

How would we read in a positive integer number from the console?

// from Chapter 4/code/pattern_match.rs 
let mut buf = String::new(); 
io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf) 
              .ok() 
              .expect("Failed to read number"); 
   let input_num: Result<u32, _> = buf.trim().parse(); 

We read the number in from the console in a String buffer buf and function trim() the value; the function expect() will show us the message if something goes wrong. But what we have read in this is still a String, we must convert that String to a number.

The method parse() tries to convert the input to an unsigned 32-bit integer in this case. What it returns is in fact again a value Result, this can either be an integer (Ok<u32>), or an error (Err) when the conversion fails.

We will encounter more examples of Option and Result in the section Generics in Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling.

Testing for failure

However, in most cases, we would like to attempt to recover from the error and let the program continue. We have already seen the basic techniques used in Rust to do just this in the Result and Option section in Chapter 4, Structuring Data and Matching Patterns, and in the section Generic data structures and functions in this chapter.

Both the Option and Result types are generic types:

The Option<T> enum can be used when we expect a value, at which point a Some(T) value is given, and a None value is returned when there was no value or in the failure case. In this way Rust forces nothingness to appear in a clear and syntactically identifiable form, leaving no room for null pointer runtime errors.
The Result<T, E> enum can be used to return an Ok(T) value in the normal (success) case, and an Err(E) value in the failure case, containing info on the error.

It is used when a computation should return a result, but it can also return an error if something went wrong. The Result type is defined with two generic types T and E as:

enum Result<T, E> { 
    Ok(T), 
    Err(E) 
} 

It again shows Rust's commitment to being on the safe side: if it's OK, give back a value of type T, if there is a problem, then give back the error which is a value of type E (usually an error message string). So, we could read them also as: OK(what) and Err(why), where what has type T and why has type E.

In the following example, we use the Result type to safely read in a value from the keyboard:

let input_num: Result<u32, _> = buf.trim().parse(); 

In other languages, like Java or C#, parsing the input to a number could result in an exception (when the input contains non-numeric characters or when it is nothing or null), and you would have to use a resource heavy try or catch construct to deal with it.

In Rust, the result of the parse() function is a Result type, and we simply test the return value of Result with a match as in line (1) in the following code, which is a much simpler mechanism.

Here is the complete code:

// see code in Chapter 5/code/input_number.rs 
use std::io; 
 
fn main() { 
  println!("Give an integer number bigger than 0:"); 
  let mut buf = String::new(); 
  io::stdin().read_line(&mut buf) 
      .ok() 
      .expect("Failed to read line"); 
  let input_num: Result<u32, _>  = buf.trim().parse(); 
  let res = match input_num {                             // (1)
        Ok(num) => num, 
        Err(_) => 0 
    }; 
    if res != 0 { 
        println!("{}, that's a beautiful number", res); 
    } 
    else { 
 println!("The input was not correct: {:?} ",  input_num); 
    } 
} 

We captured the result variable num in a new variable, using a let binding on the match:

let res = match input_num { 
      Ok(num) => num, 
      Err(_) => 0 
}; 

This prints out the input number or an error message if the input is incorrect.

Raw pointers

In unsafe code blocks, Rust allows the use of a new kind of pointers called raw pointers. These pointers have no built-in security, but you can work with them with the same freedom as you would with C pointers. They are written as:

*const T for a pointer to an immutable value, or type T
*mut T for a mutable pointer

These can point to invalid memory, and the memory resources need to be manually freed. This means that a raw pointer could inadvertently be used after freeing the memory it points to. Also, multiple concurrent threads have non-exclusive access to mutable raw pointers. Because you're not sure of its contents (at least, we have no compiler guarantee of valid content), dereferencing a raw pointer can also lead to program failure.

This is why dereferencing a raw pointer can only be done inside an unsafe block, as illustrated in the following code fragment:

// code from Chapter 10/code/raw_pointers.rs: 
let p_raw: *const u32 = &10; 
// let n = *p_raw; // compiler error! 
unsafe { 
     let n = *p_raw; 
      println!("{}", n); // prints 10 
} 

If you try to do this in normal code, you get the error:

 error: dereference of unsafe pointer requires unsafe function or block [E0133]

We can make raw pointers safe outside of references, implicitly or explicitly, with & as *const, as in the following snippet:

   let gr: f32 = 1.618; 
   let p_imm: *const f32 = &gr as *const f32; // explicit cast 
   let mut m: f32 = 3.14; 
   let p_mut: *mut f32 = &mut m; // implicit cast

However, converting a raw pointer to a reference, which should be done through the &* (address of a dereference) operation, must be done within an unsafe block:

unsafe { 
     let ref_imm: &f32 = &*p_imm;     let ref_mut: &mut f32 = &mut *p_mut; 
   } 

It is recommended to abundantly use assert! statements inside unsafe code, to check at runtime that it is doing what you expect. For instance, before dereferencing a raw pointer ptr of unknown origin, always call assert!(!ptr.is_null()); to ensure that the pointer points to a valid memory location.

Raw pointers also allow pointer arithmetic with the offset method, but only in unsafe blocks. For the example code, see pointer_offset.rs:

fn main() { 
    let items = [1u32, 2, 3, 4]; 
    let ptr = &items[1] as *const u32; 
    println!("{}", unsafe { *ptr }); 
    println!("{}", unsafe { *ptr.offset(-1) });    
    println!("{}", unsafe { *ptr.offset(1) });
}

However, doing arithmetic with pointers, as in C, is not allowed:

    println!("{}", unsafe { ptr + 2}); 

This gives us the following compiler error:

 error: binary operation `+` cannot be applied to type `*const u32` [E0369]

Raw pointers can also be useful when defining other, more intelligent pointers. For example, they are used to implement the Rc and Arc pointer types.

Binding variables to values

Storing all values in constants is not an option. It is not good because constants live as long as the program and moreover can't change, and often we want to change values. In Rust, we can bind a value to a variable by using a let binding.

// see Chapter 2/code/bindings.rs 
fn main() { 
  let energy = 5; // value 5 is bound to variable energy 
} 

Unlike in many other languages, such as Python or Go, the semicolon,;, is needed here to end the statement. Otherwise, the compiler throws an error, as follows:

error: expected one of `.`, `;`, or an operator, found `}`

We also want to create bindings only when they are used in the rest of the program, but don't worry, the Rust compiler warns us about that. The warning looks like the following:

    
values.rs:2:6: 2:7 warning: unused variable: `energy`, #[warn(unused_variables)] on by default
    
  

For prototyping purposes, you can suppress that warning by prefixing the variable name with an _, like in let _ energy = 5; in general _ is used for variables we don't need.

Notice that in the declaration above we did not need to indicate the type. Rust infers the type of the energy variable to be an integer; the let binding triggers that. If the type is not obvious, the compiler searches in the code context where the variable gets a value or how it is used.

But giving type hints like let energy = 5u16; is also OK; that way, you help the compiler a bit by indicating the type of energy, in this case a two-byte unsigned integer.

We can use the variable energy by using it in an expression, for example assigning it to another variable, or printing it:

let copy_energy = energy; 
println!("Your energy is {}", energy);); 

Here are some other declarations:

let level_title = "Level 1"; 
let dead = false; 
let magic_number = 3.14f32; 
let empty = ();  // the value of the unit type () 

The value of the magic_number variable could also be written as 3.14_f32; the _ separates the digits from the type to improve readability.

Declarations can replace previous declarations of the same variable. Consider a statement like the following:

let energy = "Abundant"; 

It would now bind the variable energy to the value Abundant of type string. The old declaration can no longer be used and its memory is freed.

Functions

The starting point of every Rust program is itself a function fn called the main() function, which can be further subdivided into separate functions for reuse of code or better code organization. Rust doesn't care in which order these functions are defined, but it is nice to put the function main() at the start of the code to get a better overview. Rust has incorporated many features of traditional functional languages; we will see examples of that in Chapter 5, Higher Order Functions and Error-Handling.

Let's start with a basic function example:

// from Chapter 3/code/functions.rs 
fn main() { 
  let hero1 = "Pac Man"; 
  let hero2 = "Riddick"; 
  greet(hero2); 
  greet_both(hero1, hero2); 
} 
 
fn greet(name: &str) { 
  println!("Hi mighty {}, what brings you here?", name); 
} 
 
fn greet_both(name1: &str, name2: &str) { 
  greet(name1); 
  greet(name2); 
} 

This prints out the following output:

Hi mighty Riddick, what brings you here?Hi mighty Pac Man, what brings you here?Hi mighty Riddick, what brings you here?

Like variables, functions have variable snake_case names that must be unique, and their parameters (which have to be typed) are separated by commas, as in this example:

name1: &str, name2: &str 

It looks like a binding, but without the let binding. Forcing a type to the parameters was an excellent design decision as it documents the function for use by its caller code and allows type inference inside the function. The type here is &str because strings are stored on the heap (see section The stack and the heap in Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types).

The functions above don't return anything useful (in fact, they return the unit value ()), but, if we want a function to actually return a value, its type must be specified after an arrow ->, as in this example:

fn increment_power(power: i32) -> i32 { 
  println!("My power is going to increase:"); 
  power + 1 
} 
 
fn main() { 
let power = increment_power(1); // function is called 
println!(" I am now at power level: {}", power);} 

When executed, it prints an output like the following:

    My power is going to increase:
    I am now at power level: 2

The return value of a function is the value of its last expression. Note that in order to return a value, the final expression must not end with a semicolon. What happens when you do end it with a semicolon? Try it out: in this case the unit value () is returned, and the compiler gives you the following error:

    error: not all control paths return a value  

We could have written the statement return power + 1 as the last line, but that is not idiomatic code. If we wanted to return a value from the function before the last code line, we would have to write return value; as in the following:

if power < 100 { return 999 } 

If this was the last line in the function, you would write it as follows:

if power < 100 { 999 } 

A function can return only one value, but this isn't much of a limitation. If we have for example, three values, a, b, and c, to return, make one tuple (a, b, c) with them and return that. We will examine tuples in more detail in the next chapter.

A function that never returns is called a diverging function and it has return type !.

For example:

fn diverges() -> ! { 
    panic!("This function never returns!"); 
} 

It can be used as any type, for example to isolate exception handling, like in this example.

A function can be recursive; that means that the function calls itself, like in the following example:

// from Chapter 3/code/fib_procedural.rs 
fn main() { 
  let ans = fib(10); 
  println!("{}", ans); 
} 
 
fn fib(x: i64) -> i64 { 
     if x == 0 || x == 1 { return x; } 
     fib(x - 1) + fib(x - 2) 
} 

Make sure that the recursion stops by including a base case, in this example when the function is called for x equal to 1 and 0.

Functions have a type, for example, the type of the function increment_power from the previous code snippet like:

Fn(i32) -> i32 

The fn function in general denotes a function type.

In Rust, you can also write a function inside another function (called a nested function), contrary to C or Java. This should only be used for small helper functions needed locally.

As an exercise, try the following:

Knowing that if can be an expression, simplify the following function:

fn verbose(x: i32) -> &'static str { 
  let result: &'static str; 
  if x < 10 { 
    result = "less than 10"; 
  } else { 
    result = "10 or more"; 
  } 
  return result; 
} 

See code in Chapter 3\exercises\ifreturn.rs.

The static in and static str variables are a so-called lifetime indication, needed here to indicate how long the function's return value will exist. The static lifetime is the longest possible lifetime, such an object stays alive throughout the entire application, and so it is available in all of its code. We'll discuss this in detail in the section Lifetimes in Chapter 6, Using Variables and Types.

What is wrong with this function that returns the absolute of a given number in the variable x?

fn abs(x: i32) -> u32 { 
   if x > 0 { 
         x 
   } else { 
         -x 
   } 
}

Correct and test it (see the code in Chapter 3/exercises/absolute.rs).

Our first program

Let's get started by showing a welcome message to the players of our game. Open your favorite text editor (like Notepad++ or gedit) for a new file and type in the following code:

// code in Chapter1\code\welcome.rs 
fn main() { 
    println!("Welcome to the Game!"); 
} 

The steps to be performed are as follows:

Save the file as welcome.rs. The .rs extension is the standard extension of Rust code files. Source file names may not contain spaces; if they contain more than one word, you can use an underscore, _, as a separator, for example: start_game.rs.
Then compile it to native code on the command line with rustc.welcome.rs. This produces an executable program, welcome.exe, on Windows or welcome on Linux.
Run this program with welcome or./welcome to get the output:

Welcome to the Game!  

The output executable gets its name from the source file. If you want to give the executable another name, like start, compile it with the option -o output_name, as shown below:

rustc welcome.rs -o start

The rustc -O produces native code optimized for execution speed (equivalent to rustc -C opt-level=2); the most optimized code is generated for rustc -C opt-level=3.

Compiling and running are separate consecutive steps, contrary to dynamic languages like Ruby or Python where these are performed in one step.

Let's explain the code a bit. If you have already worked in a C, or Java, or C# like environment, this code will seem quite familiar. As in most languages, execution of code starts in a main() function, which is mandatory in an executable program.

In a larger project with many source files, the file containing the main() function would be called main.rs by convention.

We see that main() is a function declaration because it is preceded by the keyword fn, short and elegant like most Rust keywords. The () after main denotes the parameter list, which is empty here. The function's code is placed in a code block, surrounded by curly braces { }, where the opening brace is put by convention on the same line as the function declaration, but separated by one space. The closing brace appears after the code, in the column right beneath fn.

Our program has only one line, which is indented by four spaces to improve readability (Rust is not whitespace sensitive). This line prints the string Welcome to the Game!. Rust recognizes this as a string, because it is surrounded by double quotes " ". This string was given as argument to the println! macro (the ! indicates it is a macro and not a function). The code line ends in a semicolon, ;, as most, but not all, code lines in Rust do (see Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types).

Exercises:
Write, compile, and execute a Rust program, name.rs, that prints out your name.
What is the smallest possible program in Rust in terms of code size?

The println! macro has some nice formatting capabilities and at the same time checks when compiling whether the type of variables is correct for the applied formatting (see Chapter 2, Using Variables and Types).

Developing macros

The basic structure of a macro definition for a macro with the name mac1 is of this form:

macro_rules! mac1 { 
(pattern) => (expansion); 
(pattern) => (expansion); 
... 
} 

So, we can see that the definition of a macro is also done through a macro, namely the macro macro_rules! ;As you can see, a macro is similar to a match block, defining one or more rules for pattern matching, each rule ending on a semicolon. Every rule consists of a pattern before the => sign (also called a matcher) that is replaced with the expansion part during compilation, not while executing the code.

The macro can be called as either mac1!() or mac1![]; the braces contain the arguments.

The following macro, welcome! , expects no pattern and expands into a print statement by using the println! macro. It is trivial, but it demonstrates how macros work:

// from Chapter 8/code/macros.rs 
macro_rules! welcome { 
    () => ( 
        println!("Welcome to the Game!"); 
    ) 
} 

You can invoke it by adding a bang sign, ! , to its name:

fn main() { 
   welcome!()   
} 

This prints out the following:

Welcome to the Game!  

The pattern before => can contain an expression of the form $arg:frag:

$arg binds a meta-variable, arg, to a value when the macro is called.
Variables used inside a macro, such as $arg, are prefixed with a $ sign, to distinguish them from normal variables in code.
frag is a fragment specifier, and can be one of the following, with some examples added between "":

expr: "42" or "2 + 2" or "if true then { 1 } else { 2 }" or "f(42)"
item: "fn average() { }" or "struct Person;"
block: Is a sequence of instructions delimited by curly braces, such as "{ log(error, "hi"); return 12; }"
stmt: "let x = 3"
pat: "Some(t)" or "(17, 'a')" or "_"
ty (type): "i32" or "Vec<(char, String)>" or "&T"
ident: "x" or "42"
path: "T::SpecialA"
tt: For more global elements

You can find more information on the meaning of these fragments in the official documentation ;https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/book/first-edition/macros.html.

Any other Rust literals (tokens) that appear in a matcher must match exactly.

For example, consider the following macro, mac1:

macro_rules! mac1 { 
    ($arg:expr) => (println!("arg is {}", $arg)); 
} 

When you call mac1!(42); it will print out arg is 42.

mac1 looks at its argument, 42, as an expression (expr), and binds arg to that value.

Exercises:

Write a macro, mac2, that triples its argument. Test it out for the following arguments: 5 and 2 + 3.
Write a macro, mac3, that takes an identifier name and replaces it with a binding of that name to 42. (Hint: use $arg:ident instead of $arg:expr, ident is used for variable and function names.)
Write a macro, mac4, that when invoked like mac4!("Where am I?"); prints out start - Where am I? - end.
Write a macro says that when invoked like ;says!("Hi", "Jim"); prints out He/She says: 'Hi' to Jim.

(See the example code in Chapter 8/exercises/macro_ex.rs.)

Defining a module

Crates are the compiled entities that get distributed on machines to execute. All the code of a crate is contained in an implicit root module. This code can then be split up by the developer into code units called modules, which in fact form a hierarchy of sub-modules under the root module. That way the organization of our code can be greatly improved. An evident candidate for a module is the tests code, which we discussed in Chapter 3, Using Functions and Control Structures in the The tests module section.

Modules can also be defined inside other modules, as so-called nested modules. Modules do not get compiled individually; only crates get compiled. All module code is inserted into the crate source file before compilation starts.

In previous chapters, we used built-in modules from the std crate, such as io, str, and vec. The std crate contains many modules and functions that are used in real projects; the most common types, traits, functions, and macros (such as println!) are declared in the prelude module.

A module typically contains a collection of code items such as traits, structs, methods, other functions, and even nested modules. The module's name defines a namespace for all objects it contains. We define a module with the mod keyword and a lowercase name (like game1) as follows:

mod game1 { 
   // all of the module's code items go in here 
} 

Similar to Java, each file is a module, and for every code file the compiler defines an implicit module, even when it does not contain the mod keyword. As we will see in the Importing modules and file hierarchy section, such a code file can be imported in the current code file with mod filename;.

Suppose game1 is the name of a module that contains a function, func2. If you want to use this function in code external to this module, you would address it as game1::func2. But whether this is possible depends on the visibility of func2.

Using Rust without the Standard Library

Rust is foremost a systems programming language and because the compiler can decide when a variable's lifetime ends, no garbage collection is needed for freeing memory. So when a Rust program executes, it runs in a very lightweight runtime, providing a heap, backtraces, stack guards, unwinding of the call stack when a panic occurs, and dynamic dispatching of methods on trait objects. Also, a small amount of initialization code is run before an executable project's main function starts up.

As we have seen, the standard library gives a lot of functionality. It offers support for various features of its host system: threads, networking, heap allocation, and more. It also links to its C equivalent, which also does some runtime initialization.

But Rust can also run on much more constrained systems that do not need (or do not have) this functionality. You can leave out the standard library from the compilation altogether by using the #![no_std] attribute at the start of the crate's code. In that case, Rust's runtime is roughly equivalent to that of C, and the size of the native code is greatly reduced.

When working without the standard library, the core crate and its prelude module are automatically made available to your code. The core library provides the minimal foundation needed for all Rust code to work. It comprises the basic primitive types, traits, and macros. For an overview, see; https://doc.rust-lang.org/core/.

At present, this only works for a library crate on the Rust stable version. Compiling an executable application without the standard library on Rust stable is much more involved; we refer you to https://doc.rust-lang.org/unstable-book/language-features/lang-items.html; #using-libc for a thorough and up-to-date discussion.

Using a C library

Suppose we want to calculate the tangents of a complex number. The num crate offers this functionality; however, for the purposes of this exercise, we will call the ctanf function from the C library libm instead. This is a collection of mathematical functions implemented in C. The following code defines a complex number as a simple struct.

Warning: This code only works on OS X and Linux, not on Windows.

// code from Chapter 10/code/calling_clibrary.rs: 
#[repr(C)] 
#[derive(Copy, Clone)] 
#[derive(Debug)] 
struct Complex { 
    re: f32, 
    im: f32, 
} 
 
#[link(name = "m")]extern {   fn ctanf(z: Complex) -> Complex;} 
 
fn tan(z: Complex) -> Complex { 
    unsafe { ctanf(z) } 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    let z = Complex { re: -1., im: 1. }; // z is -1 + i 
    let z_tan = tan(z); 
    println!("the tangents of {:?} is {:?}", z, z_tan); 
} 

This program prints out the following:

the tangents of Complex { re: -1, im: 1 } is Complex { re: -0.271753, im: 1.083923 }

The #[derive(Debug)] attribute is necessary because we want to show the number in a {:?} format string. #[derive(Copy, Clone)] is needed because we want to use z in the println! statement, after we have moved it by calling tan(z).The function of #[repr(C)] is to reassure the compiler that the type we are passing to C is foreign-function safe, and it tells rustc to create a struct with the same layout as C.

The signatures of the C functions we want to use must be listed in an extern{} block. The compiler cannot check these signatures, so it is important to specify them accurately to make the correct bindings at runtime. This block can also declare global variables exported by C to be used in Rust. These must be marked with static or static mut, for example, static mut version: libc::c_int.

The extern block must be preceded by a #[link(name = "m")] attribute to link in the libm library. This instructs rustc to link to that native library so that symbols from that library are resolved.

The C call itself must evidently be done inside an unsafe {} block. This block is enveloped inside the tan(z) wrapper function, which only uses Rust types. The wrapper can be exposed as a safe interface, hiding the unsafe calls and type conversions between Rust and C types, especially C pointers. When the C code returns a resource, the Rust code must contain destructors for these values to ensure their memory is released.

When is code unsafe

There are situations in which even the Rust compiler cannot guarantee that our code will behave in a safe manner. This could occur when:

We need to program against the metal, close to the operating system, processors, and hardware
We want to work with the same amount of control as is possible in C
We delegate a part of the program execution to an unsafe language, such as C
We want to use inline assembly language

Rust allows us to do all of these, but we have to envelop this possibly dangerous code in an unsafe block:

       unsafe {
         // possibly dangerous code
       }  

This means that the programmer takes full responsibility for the code in the block. The unsafe block is a promise to the compiler that the danger does not leak out of the block. The compiler will check the code areas marked as unsafe more loosely and allow otherwise forbidden manipulations, but a number of rules in the ownership system (see Chapter 7, Ensuring Memory Safety and Pointers) still remain in place.

The clear advantage here is that problem areas now appear very well isolated; if a problem occurs, we know that it can only occur in the code areas that are marked as unsafe. Having a code base where 99 percent of the code is safe and 1 percent is unsafe is much easier to maintain than a code base with 100 percent unsafe code, as in C!

So, what can we do in an unsafe block?

Work with raw pointers, especially dereferencing (see the Raw pointers section).
Call a function in another language through an Foreign Function Interface (FFI), see the Interfacing with C section.
Use assembly code in our Rust code.
Use std::mem::transmute to convert simple types, bitwise. Here is an example of its use, transforming a string to a slice of bytes:

// code from Chapter 10/code/unsafe.rs: 
use std::mem; 
 
fn main() { 
   let v: &[u8] = unsafe {  
      mem::transmute("Gandalf")  
   }; 
   println!("{:?}", v); 
} 

This prints out [71, 97, 110, 100, 97, 108, 102].
Use (read or change) mutable static variables. This can only be done in an unsafe block; it is a very bad idea anyway. Here is an example:

   // code from Chapter 10/code/unsafe.rs: 

static mut N: i32 =  42; 
fn main() { 
// N = 108; // use of mutable static requires unsafe         // function or block 
    unsafe { 
       println!("{:?}", N );  // 42 
       N = 108; 
       println!("{:?}", N );  // 108 
    } 
} 

An unsafe block can also call unsafe functions that perform these dangerous operations, marked like this: unsafe fn dangerous() { }.

Starting with Rust

Rust is a programming language developed at Mozilla Research and backed up by a big open source community. Its development was started in 2006 by language designer Graydon Hoare. Mozilla began sponsoring it in 2009 and it was first presented officially in 2010. Work on this went through a lot of iterations, culminating in early 2015 in the first stable production, version 1.0.0, developed by the Rust Project Developers, consisting of the Rust team at Mozilla and an open source community of over 1800 contributors. Since then, Rust has developed in a steady pace; its current stable version is 1.20.0.

Rust is based on clear and solid principles. It is a systems programming language, equaling C and C++ in its capabilities. It rivals idiomatic C++ in speed, but it lets you work in a much safer way by forbidding code that could cause program crashes due to memory problems. Moreover, it makes concurrent programming and parallel execution on multi-core machines memory safe without garbage collection--it is the only language that does that. By design, Rust eliminates the corruption of shared data through concurrent access, called data races.

This chapter will present you with the main reasons why Rust's popularity and adoption are steadily increasing. Then, we'll set up a working Rust development environment.

We will cover the following:

The advantages of Rust
The trifecta of Rust--safe, fast and concurrent
The stability of Rust and its evolution
The success of Rust
Using Rust
Installing Rust
The Rust compiler
Our first program
Working with Cargo
Developer tools
The Standard Library

Concurrency and threads

A system is concurrent when several computations are executing at the same time and potentially interacting with each other. The computations can only run in parallel (that is, simultaneously) when they are executing on different cores or processors.

An executing Rust program consists of a collection of native Operating System (OS) threads; the OS is also responsible for their scheduling. The unit of computation in Rust is called a thread, which is a type defined in the std::thread module. Each thread has its own stack and local state.

Until now, our Rust programs only had one thread, the main thread, corresponding with the execution of the main() function. But a Rust program can create lots of threads to work simultaneously when needed. Each thread (not only main()) can act as a parent and generate any number of children threads.

Data can either be:

Shared across threads (see the shared mutable states through atomic types section)
Sent between threads (see the communication through channels section)

Visibility of items

Items in a module are by default only visible in the module itself; they are private to the module they are defined in. If you want to make an item callable from code external to the module, you must explicitly indicate this by prefixing the item with pub (which stands for public). In the following code, trying to call func1() is not allowed by the compiler--error: function `func1` is private:

// from Chapter 8/code/modules.rs 
mod game1 { 
    // all of the module's code items go in here 
    fn func1() { 
        println!("Am I visible?"); 
    } 
 
    pub fn func2() { 
        println!("You called func2 in game1!"); 
    } 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    // game1::func1(); // <- error! 
    game1::func2(); 
} 

Calling func2() works without any problem because it is public, and this prints out the following output:

You called func2 in game1!  

A function in a nested module can only be called if it is public, and if the nested module itself is declared public, like in this code snippet:

mod game1 { 
    // other code 
    pub mod subgame1 { 
      pub fn subfunc1() { 
         println!("You called subfunc1 in subgame1!"); 
      } 
    } 
} 
 
fn main() { 
    // other code 
    game1::subgame1::subfunc1(); 
} 

This prints out the following output:

You called subfunc1 in subgame1! 

A function in a module must be prefixed with its module name when called. This distinguishes it from another function with the same name so that no name conflict can occur.

When a struct is accessed from outside the module in which it is defined, it is only visible when it is declared with pub. Moreover, its fields are private by default, so you have to explicitly declare as public those fields that you want to be visible outside. This is the encapsulation property (also called information hiding) from traditional object-oriented languages. In the following example, the fields name and age of struct Magician belong to the public interface, but power does not:

    pub struct Magician { 
        pub name: String, 
        pub age: i32, 
        power: i32 
    } 

So, this statement:

let mag1 = game1::Magician { name: "Gandalf".to_string(), age: 725, power: 98}; 

Leads to the compiler error:

error: field `power` of struct `game1::Magician` is private.  

To summarize, Rust has only two visibility modifiers:

The default, which is only visible within the current module
pub, which is exported to the parent module

Exercise:

Does this mean we cannot make instances from a struct with private fields?
Try to think of a way around this. (Hint: think about a constructor-like new function, see Chapter 8/exercises/priv_struct.rs).

Generalizing this way of reasoning, here you can see a general way to call a private method f on a private field m_impl, the so-called Private Implementation Pattern (PIMPL):

// see Chapter 8/code/mod_private.rs 
mod library { 
  pub struct Interface {   
    m_impl: Impl    // private field 
  } 
   
  impl Interface { 
    pub fn new() -> Interface { 
      Interface{ m_impl: Impl } 
    } 
     
    pub fn f(&self){ 
      self.m_impl.f(); 
    } 
  } 
   
  struct Impl; 
   
  impl Impl { 
    fn f(&self){   // private method 
      println!("f"); 
    } 
  } 
} 
 
fn main() { 
  let o = library::Interface::new(); 
  o.f(); 
} 

This prints out f.

Global constants

Often, an application needs a few values that are in fact constants, meaning that they do not change in the course of the program. In our game, for example, the game name Monster Attack could be a constant, as could the maximum health amount, which is the number 100. We must be able to use them in the main() function or any other function in our program, so they are placed at the top of the code file. They live in the global scope of the program. Such constants are declared with the keyword static, as follows:

// see Chapter 2/code/constants1.rs 
static MAX_HEALTH: i32 = 100; 
static GAME_NAME: &str = "Monster Attack"; 
 
fn main() { 
} 

Names of constants must be in uppercase, underscores can be used to separate word parts. Their type must also be indicated; the variable MAX_HEALTH is a 32-bit integer (i32) and the variable GAME_NAME is a string (str) type. As we will discuss further, the declaration of types for variables is done in exactly the same way, although it is often optional when the compiler can infer the type from the code context.

Remember that Rust is a low-level language, so many things must be specified in detail. The & is a reference to something (it contains its memory address), here of the string.

The compiler gives us a warning, which looks like this:

warning: static item is never used: `MAX_HEALTH`, #[warn(dead_code)] on by default  

This warning does not prevent the compilation, so in this stage, we can compile to an executable constants1.exe. But the compiler is right; these objects are never used in the program's code (they are called dead code), so, in a complete program, either use them or throw them out.

It takes a while before the aspiring Rust developer starts to regard the Rust compiler as his friend, and not as an annoying machine spitting out errors and warnings. As long as you see this message at the end of the compiler output,error: aborting due to previous errors, no (new) compiled executable is made. But remember, correcting the errors eliminates runtime problems, so this can save you a lot of time otherwise wasted tracking nasty bugs. Often, the error messages are accompanied by helpful notes on how to eliminate the error. Even the warnings can point you to flaws in your code. Rust also warns us when something is declared but not used in the code that follows, like unused variables, functions, imported modules, and so on. It even warns us if we make a variable mutable (which means it's value can be changed) when it should not be, or when code doesn't get executed! The compiler does such a good job that when you reach the stage that all errors and warnings are eliminated, your program most likely will run correctly!

Besides static values, we can also use simple constant values whose value never changes. Constants always have to be typed, as shown here:

const MYPI: f32 = 3.14; 

The compiler automatically substitutes the value of the constant everywhere in the code.

Borrowing a value

On the other hand we can borrow the resource by making a (mutable) reference kl2 to klaatu with:

let kl2 = &klaatu;         // a borrow or reference 

Or:

let kl2 = &mut klaatu; // a mutable borrow or reference 

A borrow is a temporary reference, passing the address of the data structure through &. The borrowed reference can access the contents of the memory location, but does not own the value. The owner gives up full control over a borrowed value while it is being borrowed.

Now, in the case of the mutable borrow, kl2 can change the object, for instance when our alien loses a tentacle in a battle:

   kl2.n_tentacles = 14; 
   println!("{} - {}", kl2.planet, kl2.n_tentacles);  

This prints out the following output:

    Venus - 14  

But if we try to change the alien's planet through klaatu, we can do it as follows:

klaatu.planet = "Pluto".to_string(); 

We get the following error:

    error: cannot assign to `klaatu.planet` because it is borrowed  

It was indeed borrowed by the kl2 reference.

Like in everyday life, while an object is borrowed, the owner does not have access to it as it is no longer in its possession. In order to change the resource, klaatu needs to own it, without the resource being borrowed at the same time.

Rust even explains this to us with the note it adds:

    borrow of `klaatu.planet` occurs here ownership.rs:18    let kl2 = &mut klaatu;  

Because kl2 borrows the resource, Rust also even forbids us to access the instance with its former name klaatu:

println!("{} - {}", klaatu.planet, klaatu.n_tentacles); 

The compiler then throws the following error:

    error: cannot borrow `klaatu.planet` as immutable because `klaatu` is also borrowed as mutable.  

When a resource is moved or borrowed, the (original) owner can no longer use it. This prevents the memory problem that is known as a dangling pointer, which is the use of a pointer that points to an invalid memory location.

But here is a revelation: if we isolate the borrowing by kl2 in its own block, like in:

// see code in Chapter 7/code/ownership2.rs 
fn main() { 
    let mut klaatu = Alien{ planet: "Venus".to_string(),    n_tentacles: 15 }; 
    {   
      let kl2 = &mut klaatu; 
      kl2.n_tentacles = 14; 
      println!("{} - {}", kl2.planet, kl2.n_tentacles);  
// prints: Venus - 14 
    } 
}

The former problems have disappeared! After the block kl2 can no longer be used, but we can now do for example:

println!("{} - {}", klaatu.planet, klaatu.n_tentacles);
klaatu.planet = "Pluto".to_string(); 
println!("{} - {}", klaatu.planet, klaatu.n_tentacles);  

This prints the following output:

    Venus - 10
    Pluto - 10  

Why is this? Because after the closing } of the code block in which the kl2 reference was bound, its lifetime ended. The borrowing was over (a borrow has to end sometime) and klaatu reclaimed full ownership, and thus the right to change. When the compiler detects that the lifetime of the original owner klaatu eventually ends, the memory occupied by the struct instance is automatically freed.

In fact this is a general rule in Rust: whenever an object goes out of scope and it doesn't have an owner anymore, its destructor is automatically called and the resources owned by it are freed, so that there never can be any memory (or other resource) leaks. This is described in technical terms as Rust obeys the Resource Acquisition Is Initialization (RAII) rule; for more info see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Acquisition_Is_Initialization.

As we experimented in the previous section on References, a resource can be immutably borrowed many times, but while immutably borrowed, the original data can't be mutably borrowed.

Some other built-in macros

The write! macro allows you to write values into any kind of buffer, optionally using the same formatting capabilities as format! and println!. In the following example, we simply write a string to a vector:

// from Chapter 8/code/write.rs 
// in order to be able to use write! on a vector 
use std::io::Write;  
 
fn main() { 
    let mut vec1 = Vec::new(); 
    write!(&mut vec1, "test"); 
    println!("{:?}", vec1); 
} 

This prints out the following:

[116, 101, 115, 116].  

A handy macro during development is unimplemented!, which you might have already seen in generated code. You can also use it yourself as a temporary placeholder for a function body you will write later:

   // from Chapter 8/code/unimplemented.rs 
      fn main() { 
          unimplemented!(); 
      } 

It will compile just fine, but when executed it will panic:

thread 'main' panicked at 'not yet implemented'  

This indicates the code line where it found the macro. That way you won't forget to write the code!

A similar macro is called unreachable! Put this in a code location that you think will never be executed, like in the following if statement:

   // from Chapter 8/code/unreachable.rs 
   fn main() { 
       if false { 
           unreachable!(); 
       } 
       unreachable!(); 
   } 

But if it does execute, it gives you a panic to indicate that code line was nevertheless reached:

thread 'main' panicked at 'internal error: entered unreachable code'.  

Collections - using hashmaps and hashsets

Often, you need to collect a large number of data items of a given type in one data structure. Until now, we have only worked with the Vec datatype to do this, but the std::collections module contains other implementations of sequences (such as LinkedList), maps (such as HashMap), and sets (such as HashSet). In most cases, you will only need Vec and HashMap; let's examine how to work with the latter.

A HashMap <K,V> is used when you want to store pairs consisting of a key of type K and a value of type V, both of generic type. K can be a Boolean, an integer, a string, or any other type that implements the Eq and Hash traits. A HashMap enables you to very quickly look up the value attached to a certain key using a hashing algorithm, and also because the data is cached. However, the keys of a HashMap are not sorted; if you need that, use a BTreeMap. HashMap is allocated on the heap, so it is dynamically resizable, just like a Vec.

Let's store monster names together with the planets they originate from:

// code from Chapter 11/code/hashmaps.rs: 
use std::collections::HashMap; 
 
fn main() {  
    let mut monsters = HashMap::new(); 
 
    monsters.insert("Oron", "Uranus"); 
    monsters.insert("Cyclops", "Venus"); 
    monsters.insert("Rahav", "Neptune"); 
    monsters.insert("Homo Sapiens", "Earth"); 
 
    match monsters.get(&"Rahav") { 
        Some(&planet) =>  
println!("Rahav originates from: {}", planet), 
        _ => println!("Planet of Rahav unknown."), 
    } 
 
    monsters.remove(&("Homo Sapiens"));  
 
    // `HashMap::iter()` returns  
    for (monster, planet) in monsters.iter() { 
println!("Monster {} originates from planet {}", monster, planet);  
    } 
} 

This program prints out:

Rahav originates from: Neptune
Monster Rahav originates from planet Neptune
Monster Cyclops originates from planet Venus
Monster Oron originates from planet Uranus

A new HashMap with default capacity is created with HashMap::new(). insert is used to put data into it, one pair at a time. If the inserted value is new, it returns None, otherwise, it returns Some(value). To retrieve a value (here the planet on which a monster comes from), use the get method. This takes a reference to a key value and returns Option<&V>, so you have to use match to find the value. remove takes a key and removes the pair from the collection. The iter() method from HashMap returns an iterator that yields (&key, &value) pairs in arbitrary order.

If your requirement is to store unique values, such as unique monster names, HashSet guarantees that; it is in fact HashMap without values:

// code from Chapter 11/code/hashsets.rs: 
use std::collections::HashSet; 
 
fn main() { 
    let mut m1: HashSet<&str> = vec!["Cyclops", "Raven", "Gilgamesh"].into_iter().collect(); 
    let m2: HashSet<&str> = vec!["Moron", "Keshiu", "Raven"].into_iter().collect(); 
 
    m1.insert("Moron"); 
    if m1.insert("Raven") { 
        println!("New value added") 
    } 
    else { 
        println!("This value is already present") 
    } 
     
    println!("m1: {:?}", m1); 
 
println!("Intersection: {:?}", m1.intersection(&m2).collect::<Vec<_>>()); 
    println!("Union: {:?}", m1.union(&m2).collect::<Vec<_>>()); 
 println!("Difference: {:?}", m1.difference(&m2).collect::<Vec<_>>()); 
    println!("Symmetric Difference: {:?}", 
             m1.symmetric_difference(&m2).collect::<Vec<_>>()); 
} 

This program prints out:

    This value is already present
    m1: {"Raven", "Cyclops", "Gilgamesh", "Moron"}
    Intersection: ["Raven", "Moron"]
    Union: ["Raven", "Cyclops", "Gilgamesh", "Moron", "Keshiu"]
    Difference: ["Cyclops", "Gilgamesh"]
    Symmetric Difference: ["Cyclops", "Gilgamesh", "Keshiu"] 

We can construct a HashSet from a Vec using into_iter().collect(). To add new values one by one, use insert(), which returns true if the value is new, or false if it is not. If the type of the set's elements implements the Debug trait, we can print them out with the {:?} format string. Methods for the intersection, union, difference, and symmetrical difference operations are also present.

Scope of a variable and shadowing

All variables defined in the program bindings.rs have local scope delimited by the { } of the function which happens to be the main() function here, but this applies to any function. After the ending, }, they go out of scope and their memory allocation is freed.

We can even make a more limited scope inside a function by defining a code block as all code contained within a pair of curly braces { }, as in the following snippet:

// see Chapter 2/code/scope.rs 
fn main() { 
  let outer = 42; 
   { // start of code block 
        let inner = 3.14; 
        println!("block variable: {}", inner); 
        let outer = 99; // shadows the first outer variable 
        println!("block variable outer: {}", outer); 
    } // end of code block 
    println!("outer variable: {}", outer); 
} 

The preceding code gives the following output:

    block variable: 3.14
    block variable outer: 99
    outer variable: 42

A variable defined in the block (like inner) is only known inside that block. A variable in the block can also have the same name as a variable in an enclosing scope (like outer), which is replaced (shadowed) by the block variable until the block ends. What do you expect when you try to print out inner after the block? Try it out.

Why would you want to use a code block? In the section Expressions, we will see that a code block can return a value that can be bound to a variable with the let binding. A code block can also be empty as { }.

Methods on structs

All the functions defined for our struct until now are so called associated functions, they are associated with the struct and are called with the syntax:

Struct_name::ass_function() 

We can also define real methods in Rust, that are called on a struct instance and that have a reference to that instance &self as first parameter.

When a specific struct Alien attacks, we can define a method for that Alien struct like this:

fn attack(&self) { 
    println!("I attack! Your health lowers with {} damage points.", self.damage); 
} 

And call it on the function alien berserk as follows:

berserk.attack(); 

A reference to berserk object (the Alien object on which the method is invoked) is passed as &self to the method. In fact the self object is like the self object in Python or this in Java or C#. A method always has &self instance as a parameter, in contrast to a static method.

Here the object is passed immutably, but what if attacking also lowers the Alien structs own health? Let's add a second attack method:

fn attack(&self) { 
    self.health -= 10; 
} 

But Rust rejects this with two compiler errors. First it says the following:

    cannot assign to immutable field self.health  

This we can remedy by passing a mutable reference to the self instance like this:

fn attack(&mut self) 

But now Rust complains:

    duplicate definition of value 'attack'  

This means that Rust does not allow two methods with the same name, as there is no method overloading in Rust. This is because of the way type inference works.

Changing the name to attack_and_suffer, we get:

fn attack_and_suffer(&mut self, damage_from_other: u32) { 
   println!("I attack! Your health lowers with {} damage points.", self.damage); 
   self.health -= damage_from_other; 
   } 

After calling the berserk.attack_and_suffer(31); function; the berserk variables's health is now 69 (where 31 is the number of damage points inflicted upon the object berserk by another attacking Alien).

Exercise:

Complex numbers like 2 + 5i (i is the square root of -1) have a real part (here 2) and an imaginary part (5); both are floating point numbers. Define a struct Complex and some methods for it, for example: A new method to construct a complex number a to_string method that prints a complex number like 2 + 5i or 2 - 5i (hint: use the format! macro which works the same way as the println! macro but returns a string). An add method to add two complex numbers; this is a new complex number where the real part is the sum of the real parts of the operands, and the same for the imaginary part. A times_ten method that changes the object itself by multiplying both parts by 10 (hint: think carefully about the method's argument). As a bonus, make an abs method that calculates the absolute value of a complex number (see: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absolute_value) Note: If you need to work with complex numbers in a real project use the Complex struct from the num crate num::Complex (see https://rust-num.github.io/num/num/struct.Complex.html). Test your methods! (for example code see Chapter 6/exercises/complex.rs).

Lifetimes

All variables in Rust code have a lifetime, which is the area of code in which the variable is defined. Suppose we declare a variable n with the binding let n = 42u32; Such a value is valid from where it is declared to when it is no longer referenced; its lifetime ends there. This is illustrated in the following code snippet:

// see code in Chapter 7/code/lifetimes.rs    
fn main() { 
    let n = 42u32; 
    let n2 = n; // a copy of the value from n to n2 
    println!("The value of n2 is {}, the same as n", n2); 
    let p = life(n); 
    println!("p is: {}", p); // p is: 42 
    println!("{}", m);  // error: unresolved name `m`. 
    println!("{}", o);  // error: unresolved name `o`. 
} 
 
fn life(m: u32) -> u32 { 
    let o = m; 
    o 
} 

The lifetime of n ends when the main() function ends; in general the start and end of a lifetime happen in the same scope, here a function. The words lifetime and scope are synonymous, but we generally use the word lifetime for referring to the extent of a reference. As in other languages, local variables or parameters declared in a function do not exist anymore when the function has finished executing: in Rust we say their lifetime has ended. When the lifetime of a variable has ended, its memory is freed automatically, so the variable can no longer be used in the following code. This is the case for variables m and o in the code snippet mentioned earlier, which are only known in the function life.

Likewise the lifetime of a variable declared in a nested block is restricted to that block, like the phi variable in the following example:

   { 
      let phi = 1.618; 
   } 
   println!("The value of phi is {}", phi); // error 

Trying to use the phi variable when its lifetime is over results in an error:

    error: cannot find value `phi` in this scope`

The lifetime of a value can be indicated in code by an annotation and it is sometimes mandatory to do so. A lifetime is written as: 'a, which reads as: lifetime a, where a is simply an indicator; it could also be written as 'b, 'n or 'life. It's common to see single letters used to represent lifetimes. In the preceding example, an explicit lifetime indication was not necessary, since there were no references involved. All values tagged with the same lifetime have at its maximum that same lifetime.

We know this notation already from 'static, which, as we saw in Chapter 3, Using Functions And Control Structures in the section Functions, is the lifetime of things that last for the entire length of the program.

In the following example we have a function transform which explicitly declares the lifetime of its parameter s of type &str to be 'a:

fn transform<'a>(s: &'a str) { /* ... */ } 

Note the <'a> indication right after the name of the function.

In nearly all cases this explicit indication is not needed because the compiler is smart enough to deduce the lifetimes, so we could simply write:

fn transform_without_lifetime(s: &str) { /* ... */ } 

In fact, only things relating to references (such as a struct which contains a reference, or a function that has parameters that are a reference) need lifetimes.

Here is an example where, even when we indicate a lifetime specifier 'a, the compiler does not allow our code. Suppose we have defined a struct Magician as:

struct Magician { 
    name: &'static str, 
    power: u32 
} 

Here 'static is mandatory, if we leave it out, we get the error:

error[E0106]: missing lifetime specifier

If we define the following function:

fn return_magician<'a>() -> &'a Magician { 
    let mag = Magician { name: "Gandalf", power: 4625}; 
  &mag  
}

We get the following error:

error: `mag` does not live long enough

Why is this? The lifetime of the mag value ends when the function return_magician ends, but nevertheless this function tries to return a reference to that Magician value, which no longer exists. Such an invalid reference is known as a dangling pointer. This is a situation which clearly would lead to errors and cannot be allowed.

The lifetime of a pointer must always be shorter or equal than that of the value which it points to, thus avoiding dangling (or null) references.

In some situations the decision of whether the lifetime of an object has ended is complicated, but in almost all cases the borrow checker does this for us automatically by inserting lifetime annotations in the intermediate code, so we don't have to. This is known as lifetime elision.

For example, when working with structs, we can safely assume that the struct instance and its fields have the same lifetime. Only when the borrow checker is not completely sure it can happen do we need to indicate the lifetime explicitly, but this happens only on rare occasions, mostly when references are returned.

One example is when we have a struct with fields that are references. This code won't compile:

struct MagicNumbers { 
    magn1: &u32, 
    magn2: &u32 
} 

And gives us an error again:

error[E0106]: missing lifetime specifier 

We have to change it to the following:

struct MagicNumbers<'a> { 
    magn1: &'a u32, 
    magn2: &'a u32 
} 

This is to specify that both the struct and the fields have the same lifetime 'a.

Exercise:

Explain why the following code won't compile:
// see code in Chapter 7/exercises/dangling_pointer.rs:
fn main() {
let m: &u32 = { let n = &5u32; &*n };
let o = *m; }

Same question for this code snippet:
let mut x = &3; { let mut y = 4; x = &y; }

And this snippet:
struct IntNumber<'a> {
x: &'a i32,
}
let x = 1;
{ | let y = &5;
let f = IntNumber { x: y };
x = &f.x; } println!("{}", x);

Carefully read the error messages and the hints to what is wrong and how it could be solved.

Thread safety

Traditional programming with threads is very difficult to get right if you allow the different threads to work on the same mutable data, or so-called shared memory. When two or more threads simultaneously change data, then data corruption (also called data racing) can occur due to the unpredictability of the thread's scheduling.

In general, data (or a type) is said to be thread-safe when its contents will not be corrupted by the execution of different threads. Other languages offer no such help, but the Rust compiler simply forbids non-thread-safe situations to occur. The same ownership strategy that we looked at to allow Rust to prevent memory safety errors also enables you to write safe, concurrent programs.

Consider the following program:

// code from Chapter 9/code/not_shared.rs:    
use std::thread; 
use std::time; 
 
fn main() { 
    let mut health = 12; 
    for i in 2..5 { 
        thread::spawn(move || { 
            health *= i; 
        }); 
    } 
 thread::sleep(time::Duration::from_secs(2)); 
    println!("{}", health); // 12 
} 

Our initial health is 12, but there are three fairies that can double, triple, and quadruple our health. We let each of them do that in a different thread, and after the threads are finished we expect a health of 288 (= 12 * 2 * 3 * 4). But after their magic actions, our health is still 12, even if we wait long enough to be sure that the threads are finished. Clearly, the three threads worked on a copy of our variable, not on the variable itself. Rust does not allow the health variable to be shared among the threads to prevent data corruption. In the next section, we will explore how we can use mutable variables that are shared between threads.

Associated functions on structs

Rust makes it possible to call a method in two ways. For example, when we want to obtain the length of a string, you can do:

// see code in Chapter 6/code/paradigm.rs 
let str1 = "abc"; 
println!("{}", str::len(str1)); // 3 
println!("{}", str1.len());     // 3 

The first way is procedural and calls the len function from the str crate in the standard library and passes the string slice str1 as a parameter. The second way which is more object-oriented and more commonly used calls the len method on the string slice str1. If you look it up in the API docs, you can see it has the signature:

   fn len(&self) -> usize 

It effectively takes a reference (&) to self as a parameter.

So we see that Rust caters also for more object-oriented developers, who are used to the object.method() type of notation instead of function(object) type of notation. In Rust, we can define associated functions and methods on a struct, which pretty much compares to the traditional class and methods concept.

Suppose we are building a game that takes place on a planet in a distant solar system, inhabited by hostile aliens. Let's define a struct Alien like this:

// see code in Chapter 6/code/methods.rs 
struct Alien { 
   health: u32, 
   damage: u32 
} 

Where the variable health is the Alien struct's condition, and the variable damage is the amount your health is decreased when the alien attacks. We could make an Alien like this:

let mut bork = Alien{ health: 100, damage: 5 }; 

The variable health cannot be more than 100, but we cannot impose this constraint when making a struct instance like this.

A solution is to define a new function for the Alien implementor, where we can test the value before it is being set:

impl Alien { 
   fn new(mut h: u32, d: u32) -> Alien { 
      // constraints: 
      if h > 100 { h = 100; } 
      Alien {health: h, damage: d} 
   } 
}   

And then construct a new Alien as follows:

let mut berserk = Alien::new(150, 15); 

We define the new function (and all other functions and methods on the implementor Alien) inside an impl Alien block, which is separate from the Alien struct definition. It returns an Alien object after all constraints have been applied. We call it on the Alien struct itself as Alien::new(). It is a static function because we don't call it on an Alien strcuct instance.

If we look at our new Alien struct, we see that the constraint was imposed:

println!("The berserk's health at birth is: {}", berserk.health); 

This has the output as follows:

    The berserk's health at birth is: 100.  

Such a new function closely resembles a constructor from object-oriented languages. The fact that it is called new is merely by convention, we could have called it as the create(), or the give_birth() function.

Another static function could be a warning given by all aliens:

fn warn() -> &'static str { 
    "Leave this planet immediately or perish!" 
} 

This can be called like this:

println!("{}", Alien::warn()); 

And this outputs the message:

    Leave this planet immediately or perish!

The try! macro and the ? operator

When, during a computation, several function calls return a Result type value, the handling of the error propagation through pattern matching can become quite tedious-each returned Result type value requires a match to differentiate between an Ok value and an Err value.

We had exactly such a situation in the input_number.rs program, where we read an input from the terminal and tried to parse it into an unsigned integer, both operations can fail.

The try! macro was specifically made in order to simplify such code and make error-handling more elegant and readable.

The try! macro can only be used from inside a function that returns a Result type value, so not from within the main() function. Also, it can only be used on functions that return a Result type value. It returns the Ok value, and then continues with the function's code. But in case of an error the Err value is returned, returning immediately from the enclosing function. If we apply this to input_number.rs, we get much more readable code, as follows:

// see code in Chapter 5/code/try_input_number.rs 
use std::io; 
use std::error; 
 
fn main() { 
    println!("Give a positive secret number: "); 
    match input_num() { 
        Ok(v) => println!("Input value is: {}", v), 
  Err(e) => println!("Error - Please input an integer number!: {}", e) 
    } 
} 
 
fn input_num() -> Result<u32, Box<error::Error>> { 
    let mut input = String::new(); 
    try!(io::stdin().read_line(&mut input)); 
    Ok(try!(input.trim().parse())) 
} 

When there is no input, the program prints out the following error:

    Error - Please input an integer number!: cannot parse integer from empty string  

Then, the program exits normally. When a non-digit input is given, the program prints out to give a positive secret number, as follows:

    Error - Please input an integer number!: invalid digit found in string  

Then, it exits normally.

The dangerous operations are wrapped inside the function input_num. We can use the try! macro on these operations because the input_num function returns a Result type value.

Our code becomes even shorter when we use the error propagation operator ?, which works the same way as the try! macro:

  fn input_num() -> Result<u32, Box<error::Error>> { 
       let mut input = String::new(); 
    io::stdin().read_line(&mut input)?; 
    Ok(input.trim().parse()?) 
} 

The Box<error::Error>> is a so called boxed pointer, a reference to an Error instance from the std::error module. We talk more about the Box pointer in Chapter 7, Ensuring Memory Safety and Pointers. We need to use a Box pointer here to let the compiler know that we don't know the size of the error instance.

If all you need from errors is their string content, you could simplify error-handling by using the simple error crate (https://crates.io/crates/simple-error).

Building crates

At the highest level, there is the crate. The Rust distribution contains a number of crates, such as the std crate of the standard library, which we have already used often. Other built-in crates include the collections crate, with functionality to work with strings, vectors, linked lists, and key-value maps, and the test or rustc-test crates, with unit-testing and micro-benchmarking functionality.

A crate is the equivalent of a package or library in other languages. It is also the unit of compilation: rustc only compiles one crate at a time. What does this mean? When our project has a code file containing a main() function, then it is clear that our project is an executable program (also called a binary), starting execution in main(). For example, if we compile structs.rs as follows:

rustc structs.rs  

A .exe file, structs.exe, is produced in Windows, which can be executed on its own (and equivalent structs executables on other operating systems). This is the standard behavior when invoking rustc. When working with Cargo (see Chapter 1, Starting with Rust) we have to indicate that we want a binary project at its creation with the --bin flag:

cargo new projname --bin

However, often you want to write a project whose code will be called from other projects, a so-called shared library (in Windows this is a .dll file, in Linux an .so file, and on OSX a .dylib file). In that case, your code will only contain data structures and functions to work on them, so you must explicitly indicate this to the compiler using the --crate-type flag with the lib option:

rustc --crate-type=lib  structs.rs  

The resulting file is far smaller in size and is called libstructs.rlib; the suffix is now .rlib (for Rust library) and lib is prepended before the filename. If you want the crate to have another name, like mycrate, then use the --crate-name flag as follows:

rustc --crate-type=lib  --crate-name=mycrate  structs.rs  

This creates a libmycrate.rlib as the output file.

An alternative to using the rustc flags is to put this info as the attributes at the top of the code file, like this:

// from Chapter 8/code/structs.rs 
#![crate_type = "lib"]  
#![crate_name = "mycrate"] 

The crate_type attribute can take the following values: bin, lib, rlib, dylib, and staticlib, according to whether you want a binary executable or a library of a certain type, dynamically or statically linked (in general when an attr attribute applies to a whole crate, the syntax to use in code is #![crate_attr]).

Each library used in an application is a separate crate. In any case, you need an executable (binary) crate that uses the library crates.

Rust has a built-in library manager called Cargo (for more info on Cargo, see Chapter 1, Starting with Rust, and the Working with Cargo section); it creates a library project by default. Typically, when starting your own project, you would create it with Cargo, use the code organization techniques you will learn in this chapter, and then make this code into an executable with:

cargo build  

You can install other crates into your project from the crates repository https://crates.io; in the Adding external crates to a project section, we see how this is done.

Traits

What if our game is really diversely populated, and besides Aliens we have also Zombies and Predators, and, needless to say, they all want to attack. Can we abstract their common behavior into something they all share? Of course, in Rust we say that they have a trait in common, analogous to an interface or superclass in other languages. Let's call that trait Monster, and because they all want to attack, a first version could be:

// see code in Chapter 6/code/traits.rs 
trait Monster { 
    fn attack(&self); 
} 

A trait mostly contains a description of methods, that is, their type declarations or signatures, but no real implementation (as we will see later in the example, a trait can contain a default implementation of a method). This is logical, because Zombies, Predators, and Aliens could each have their own method of attack. So there is no code body between {} after the function signature, but don't forget the ;(semicolon) to close it off.

When we want to implement the Monster trait for the struct Alien, we write the following code:

impl Monster for Alien { 
 
} 

When we compile this, Rust throws the following error:

    not all trait items implemented, missing: `attack`  

That's useful because Rust reminds us which methods from a trait we have forgotten to implement. The following code would make it pass:

impl Monster for Alien { 
   fn attack(&self) { 
println!("I attack! Your health lowers with {} damage points.", self.damage); 
   } 
} 

So the trait implementation for a type must provide the real code, which is executed when that method is called on an Alien struct object. If a Zombie struct attack is twice as bad, its Monster implementation could be:

impl Monster for Zombie { 
   fn attack(&self) { 
println!("I bite you! Your health lowers with {} damage points.", 2 * self.damage); 
   } 
} 

We could add other functions and methods to our trait, such as a new, a noise, and an attack_with_sound method:

trait Monster { 
    fn new(hlt: u32, dam: u32) -> Self; 
    fn attack(&self); 
    fn noise(&self) -> &'static str; 
    fn attacks_with_sound(&self) { 
println!("The Monster attacks by making an awkward sound {}", self.noise()); 
    } 
} 

Notice that in the new method the resulting object is of Self type, which becomes the Alien implementor type or Zombie in a real implementation of the trait.

Methods differ from functions because they have an &self instance as parameter, that means they have the object on which they are invoked as parameter, for example:

fn noise(&self) -> &'static str 

When we call it with the zmb1.noise() function, the object zmb1 becomes a self type.

A trait can provide default code for a method (like here for the attack_with_sound method). The implementor type can choose to take this default code or override it with its own version. Code in a trait method can also call upon other methods in the trait with the method self.method(), as in the attack_with_sound method where the self.noise() method is called.

The full implementation of the Monster trait for type Zombie could then be:

impl Monster for Zombie { 
   fn new(mut h: u32, d: u32) -> Zombie { 
      // constraints: 
      if h > 100 { h = 100; } 
      Zombie {health: h, damage: d} 
   } 
 
   fn attack(&self) { 
println!("The Zombie bites! Your health lowers with {} damage points.", 2 * self.damage); 
   } 
 
   fn noise(&self) -> &'static str { 
      "Aaargh!" 
   } 
} 

And here is a short fragment of our game scenario:

let zmb1 = Zombie {health: 75, damage: 15}; 
println!("Oh no, I hear: {}", zmb1.noise()); 
zmb1.attack(); 

This prints the following output:

    Oh no, I hear: Aaargh!
    The Zombie bites! Your health lowers with 30 damage points.  

Traits are not limited to structs, they can be implemented on any type. A type can also implement many different traits. All the different implemented methods are compiled to a version specific for their type, so after compilation there exists a different new method for the Alien, Zombie, and Predator trait.

Implementing all of the methods in a trait can be tedious work. For example, we probably want to be able to show our creatures in this way:

println!("{:?}", zmb1); 

Unfortunately this gives us the compiler error:

    error[E0277]: the trait bound `Zombie: std::fmt::Debug` is not satisfied.  

So from the message we can infer that this {:?} format string uses a trait Debug. If we look this up in the docs we find that we must implement an fmt method (specifying a way to format the data from the struct instance). But the compiler once again helps us out here: if we prefix our Zombie struct definition with #[derive(Debug)], then a default code version is generated automatically!

#[derive(Debug)] 
struct Zombie { health: u32, damage: u32 } 

So that println!("{:?}", zmb1); now shows:

    Zombie { health: 75, damage: 15 }  

This mechanism also works for a whole list of other traits (see section Built-in traits and http://rustbyexample.com/trait/derive.html).

The actual implementation of a trait for a type is separated from the definition of the type itself: the data and the operations on them are independent. They can reside in different files, or even different modules, providing for more flexibility.